<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>BHOLE</title>
    <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes" />
    <updated>2021-01-11T09:31:11-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>William Slattery</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes</id>

    <entry>
        <title>NMS03 - Principles of Neurobiology II</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/nms03-principles-of-neurobiology-ii.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/nms03-principles-of-neurobiology-ii.html</id>

        <updated>2021-01-11T09:31:11-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    LOsDefine and use following terms: circuit/pathway, decussation, lesion, primary/secondary/tertiary neurons, homunculus Describe in broad detail the pathway for detecting pain from the body, and how primary sensationis only one part of experiencing pain. Describe the homunculus and its use. Describe the limbic system and its&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2 id="los">LOs</h2>
<ol>
<li><p>Define and use following terms: circuit/pathway, decussation, lesion, primary/secondary/tertiary 
neurons, homunculus</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#principles-of-neurobiology">Circuit/Pathway:</a> Functions of the nervous system rely on multiple, interconnected gray and white matter structures
working together in a circuit. Function requires intact circuits. Damage to any part or to connections between parts breaks the
circuit and overall function is lost or damaged.</li>
<li><a href="#principles-of-neurobiology">Decussation:</a> Decussation is the movement of a signal from one side of the body to the 
contralateral side of the brain.</li>
<li><a href="#principles-of-neurobiology">Lesion:</a> area of abnormal tissue.</li>
<li><a href="#pain">Neurons:</a><ul>
<li>Primary: Enters from periphery into proximal portion of dorsal horn where it activates a synapse.</li>
<li>Secondary: Secondary neuron crosses midline and ascends up through a tract and through the 
brainstem to the thalamus</li>
<li>Tertiary Neurons: At the thalamus, secondary synapse onto tertiary neurons. This synapse 
allows for modulation</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#homunculus">Homunculus:</a> Somatosensory and Motor homunculus are a artistic representation of cortex body 
mapping</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="#pain">Describe in broad detail the pathway for detecting pain from the body, and how primary sensation
is only one part of experiencing pain.</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Pain enters from periphery and travels along the distal portion of a <em>primary neuron</em> into the proximal
portion located in the dorsal horn.</li>
<li>Primary activates a synapse in the dorsal horn, which allows for a reflex response and modulation.<ul>
<li>Reflexes elicit a movement away from the painful thing before the pain is even processed by CNS</li>
<li>Synapse allows for modulation (intensity) of the painful signal (ascending/descending) </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Secondary neuron crosses midline and ascends up through a tract and through the brainstem to the
thalamus</li>
<li>At the thalamus, secondary synapse onto tertiary neurons. This synapse allows for modulation.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="#homunculus">Describe the homunculus and its use.</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Somatosensory and Motor homunculus are a artistic representation of cortex body 
mapping</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="#limbic-system">Describe the limbic system and its broad functions</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Connects primary cortex stimuli to <em>context</em>.</li>
<li>Cingulate Gyrus: C-shaped, involved in <em>emotional</em> feeling.</li>
<li>Amygdala and hippocampus: <em>learning</em> pain as well as <em>recall</em>.</li>
<li>Hypothalamus: Evoke ‘fight or flight’ response</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="#shared-processing---movement">Describe three major components of healthy movement and the nervous system structures associated
with each.</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Nervous system needs to make muscles contract. <em>Corticospinal tract</em></li>
<li>Contractions occur when you want, and not when you dont. <em>Basal Ganglia</em></li>
<li>Contractions add up to complex movment should flow from one to another fluidly. <em>Cerebellum</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<h3 id="pain">Pain:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Pain enters from periphery and travels along the distal portion of a <em>primary neuron</em> into the proximal
portion located in the dorsal horn.</li>
<li>Primary activates a synapse in the dorsal horn, which allows for a reflex response and modulation.<ul>
<li>Reflexes elicit a movement away from the painful thing before the pain is even processed by CNS</li>
<li>Synapse allows for modulation (intensity) of the painful signal (ascending/descending) </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Secondary neuron crosses midline and ascends up through a tract and through the brainstem to the
thalamus</li>
<li>At the thalamus, secondary synapse onto tertiary neurons. This synapse allows for modulation.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="homunculus">Homunculus</h3>
<ul>
<li>All inputs and outputs of the cortex are bodymapped.</li>
<li>Somatosensory and Motor homunculus are a artistic representation of cortex body mapping.
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/18/homonc.png" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/18/responsive/homonc-xs.png 300w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/18/responsive/homonc-sm.png 480w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/18/responsive/homonc-md.png 768w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/18/responsive/homonc-lg.png 1024w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/18/responsive/homonc-xl.png 1360w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/18/responsive/homonc-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="Image description" width="433" height="499" /></figure></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="primary-sensation-vs-pain">Primary Sensation vs “Pain”</h3>
<ul>
<li>Primary cortex detects a stimulus and informs other cortex, adding context to the signal.</li>
<li><em>Limbic System</em> </li>
</ul>
<h3 id="limbic-system">Limbic System</h3>
<ul>
<li>Connects primary cortex stimuli to <em>context</em>.</li>
<li>Cingulate Gyrus: C-shaped, involved in <em>emotional</em> feeling.</li>
<li>Amygdala and hippocampus: <em>learning</em> pain as well as <em>recall</em>.</li>
<li>Hypothalamus: Evoke ‘fight or flight’ response</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="principles-of-neurobiology">Principles of Neurobiology</h3>
<ul>
<li>Functions of the nervous system rely on multiple, interconnected gray and white matter structures
working together in a circuit.</li>
<li>Function requires intact circuits. Damage to any part or to connections between parts breaks the
circuit and overall function is lost or damaged.</li>
<li>Decussation is the movement of a signal from one side of the body to the contralateral side of
the brain. Pain decussates immediately, but not all pathways decussate immediately. Fine touch
pathway ascends to the brainstem BEFORE it decussates.</li>
<li>Any signals going to the cortex will have to pass through thalamus first.</li>
<li>Inputs and outputs of the brain are body-mapped.</li>
<li>Shared processing is essential for full effect. </li>
<li>Lesions: area of abnormal tissue.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="shared-processing---movement">Shared Processing - Movement</h3>
<ul>
<li>Nervous system needs to make muscles contract. <em>Corticospinal tract</em></li>
<li>Contractions occur when you want, and not when you dont. <em>Basal Ganglia</em></li>
<li>Contractions add up to complex movment should flow from one to another fluidly. <em>Cerebellum</em></li>
</ul>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>NMS02 - Principles of Neurobiology</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/02-principles-of-neurobiology.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/02-principles-of-neurobiology.html</id>

        <updated>2021-01-11T08:57:11-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    LOsDescribe parts of neuron List major structures that comprise CNS and PNS. Describe the difference in terminology for grayand white matter between those two divisions. Define and use following terms: nucleus, ganglion, tract, nerve, gray matter, white matter, cortex, sub-cortical, modality, neuraxis Identify and describe&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2 id="los">LOs</h2>
<ol>
<li><p><a href="#neurons">Describe parts of neuron</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Dendrites rx, axon tx, synapse in connection between. soma keeps the cell alive.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="#divisions">List major structures that comprise CNS and PNS. Describe the difference in terminology for gray
and white matter between those two divisions.</a></p>
<ul>
<li>CNS: Brain, brainstem, spinal cord.</li>
<li>PNS: Spinal nerves, cranial nerves</li>
<li>Grey: neuronal cell bodies. Spine has a grey chewy center.</li>
<li>White: Myelinated axons. Brain has a white chewy center</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="#divisions">Define and use following terms: nucleus, ganglion, tract, nerve, gray matter, white matter, 
cortex, sub-cortical, modality, neuraxis</a></p>
<ul>
<li>Nucleus:  CNS a collection of neuronal cell bodies</li>
<li>Ganglion: PNS a collection of neuronal cell bodies</li>
<li>Tract: CNS a bundle of axons</li>
<li>Nerve: PNS a bundle of axons</li>
<li>Gray Matter: neuronal cell bodies</li>
<li>White Matter: Myelinated axons</li>
<li><a href="#lobes-of-cerebral-cortex">Cortex:</a> Multi-layered quilts of neurons surrounding hemispheres</li>
<li><a href="#examples-of-sub-cortical-gray-matter">Sub-cortical:</a> Deeper within grey matter beneath cortex. Cerebellum, Basal Ganglia, Thalamus, 
Hypothalamus</li>
<li><a href="#modality">Modality:</a> A type of information that is sent to CNS. <ul>
<li>Sensory:(pain, touch, visual, auditory)</li>
<li>Cognitive: Process sensory using context of memories, emotions, expectations</li>
<li>Behavioral: Govern state of the brain (sleep, awareness, emotional state, motivation)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Neuraxis: Rostral, Caudal, Dorsal, Ventral. Remember a 90* bend after spine.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="#spinal-cord">Identify and describe major parts of spinal cord, brainstem, and brain.</a></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#spinal-cord">Spinal cord:</a><ul>
<li>Extends from lowest part of brainstem. It controls body and limbs.
Contains white matter bundles that run up/down, as well as a core of cell bodies.</li>
<li>Dorsal Root Ganglion: White matter structure that links peripheral sensory to CNS</li>
<li>Ventral Root: White matter that carries motor bundles.</li>
<li>Dorsal Horn: Grey matter that contains sensory bundles.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#brainstem">Brainstem:</a><ul>
<li>Midbrain</li>
<li>Pons</li>
<li>Medulla - physically connects to spinal cord</li>
<li>Brainstem is a conduit for fibers from brain to spinal cord</li>
<li>Home to gray matter that carries out motor commands to and sensation from, the head and neck.</li>
<li>Home to life-sustaining functions such as breathing, cardiac function, and consciousness.</li>
<li>In the spine we had grey matter on the inside, white on the outside. Within brain this gets 
intermingled.</li>
<li><a href="#brain">Brain:</a></li>
<li>Two cerebral hemispheres. Physically identical, but functionally not.</li>
<li>Contralateral control.</li>
<li>Each is covered with a multi-layered quilts of neurons called a cortex</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>List planes of sections and directional terms used for CNS. Describe structures in relation to
one another using correct terminology. Be able to identify coronal, sagittal, and horizontal sections.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<h3 id="neurons">Neurons:</h3>
<p>Dendrites receive. Soma keeps neuron alive. Axons communicate. And a synapse is the connection spot
between axon and dendrite.</p>
<h3 id="divisions">Divisions:</h3>
<ul>
<li>CNS: Brain, brainstem, spinal cord</li>
<li>PNS: Spinal nerves, cranial nerves</li>
<li>Both contain gray and white matter. Gray = neuronal cell bodies, white = myelinated axons.</li>
<li>In CNS a collection of neuronal cell bodies is called a nucleus.</li>
<li>In PNS a collection of neuronal cell bodies is called a ganglion.</li>
<li>In CNS a bundle of axons can be called: tract, lemniscus, column, fasciculus, funiculus, etc.</li>
<li>In PNS it can be called a nerve, ramus, cord, etc.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="modality">Modality:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Sensory systems - input to CNS in multiple modalities. Modality is a type of information like touch
, pain, visual, etc.</li>
<li>Cognitive systems - process incoming sensory information in the context of memories, emotions,
expectations, plans.</li>
<li>Behavioral systems - govern state of the brain ie. sleep, awareness, emotional state, motivation</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="output">Output:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Somatic motor</li>
<li>Autonomic (visceral motor)</li>
<li>Neuroendocrine (homeostatic)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="spinal-cord">Spinal Cord:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Extends from lowest part of brainstem</li>
<li>Allow brain and brainstem to control body/limbs</li>
<li>Contain white matter bundles that run up and down, as well as a core of cell bodies</li>
<li>Dorsal Root Ganglion: Dorsal Root is a white matter structure that links sensory to CNS</li>
<li>Ventral Root: White matter. Motor</li>
<li>Dorsal Horn: Grey matter</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="brainstem">Brainstem:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Midbrain</li>
<li>Pons</li>
<li>Medulla - physically connects to spinal cord</li>
<li>Brainstem is a conduit for fibers from brain to spinal cord</li>
<li>Home to gray matter that carries out motor commands to and sensation from, the head and neck.</li>
<li>Home to life-sustaining functions such as breathing, cardiac function, and consciousness.</li>
<li>In the spine we had grey matter on the inside, white on the outside. Within brain this gets 
intermingled.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="brain">Brain:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Two cerebral hemispheres. Physically identical, but functionally not.</li>
<li>Contralateral control.</li>
<li>Each is covered with a multi-layered quilts of neurons called a cortex</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="lobes-of-cerebral-cortex">Lobes of Cerebral Cortex:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Frontal: Primary motor cortex/executive functions (decision-making, logic)</li>
<li>Parietal: Somatosensory cortex</li>
<li>Temporal: Auditory cortex</li>
<li>Occipital: Visual cortex</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="hemispheric-contents">Hemispheric Contents:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Cortex has ridges (gyri) and valleys (sulci)</li>
<li>Cortex connected to itself and other structures by network of white matter bundles inside each 
hemisphere.</li>
<li>More gray matter nuclei (sub-cortical grey matter) within the cortex</li>
<li>Corpus callosum is a sub-cortical white matter bridge between left and right hemispheres.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="examples-of-sub-cortical-gray-matter">Examples of sub-cortical gray matter:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Thalamus: gateway to cortex, one on each side</li>
<li>Hypothalamus: maintains homeostasis, controls autonomic, and endocrine function</li>
<li>Basal Ganglia: Caudate, putamen, globus pallidus</li>
<li>Cerebellum: ‘little brain’</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="grey-and-white-matter-in-cns">Grey and White matter in CNS:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Within the hemispheres the (cortical) grey matter is on the outside, 
and the white matter is deep.</li>
<li>Subcortical structures are dotted within this deep white matter.</li>
<li>Within the brain stem the grey and white matter is more mixed up and intermingled.</li>
<li>Within the spinal cord the grey matter is deep, making the horned butterfly shape, surrounded by 
white.</li>
<li>There is a fluid filled <em>ventricular system</em> within the hemispheres. They produce and circulate
CSF. Always next to caudate nucleus.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="planes-of-section">Planes of Section</h3>
<ul>
<li>Horizontal, Coronal, Sagittal</li>
<li>Remember, for spine rostral = top of head and for brain rostral = beak/face</li>
</ul>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Virology VII</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-vii.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-vii.html</id>
            <category term="MMG"/>

        <updated>2020-12-06T17:14:54-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Family RetroviridaeMorphologySpeciesStructureProviral GenomeLife CycleTransmissionPathogenesisClinical ManifestationClinically Dormant Stage - LatencyHIV set pointTime CourseOpportunistic InfectionsNeurological DiseaseDiagnosticsHIV Antiviral ModelsBindingFusion InhibNucleoside Analogue Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors: NRTIsnon-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs)Integrase InhibitorsProtease InhibitorsHighly Active Antiretroviral Therapy, or HAARTConsiderations When Choosing HAARTTreatment FailureImmune Reconsitution SyndromeTruvada - ProphylaxisHTLVFamily RetroviridaeAlpha-Epsilonretrovirus and LentivirusLentivirusSpecies: HIV-1&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <ul>
<li><a href="#family-retroviridae">Family Retroviridae</a><ul>
<li><a href="#morphology">Morphology</a></li>
<li><a href="#species">Species</a></li>
<li><a href="#structure">Structure</a></li>
<li><a href="#proviral-genome">Proviral Genome</a></li>
<li><a href="#life-cycle">Life Cycle</a></li>
<li><a href="#transmission">Transmission</a></li>
<li><a href="#pathogenesis">Pathogenesis</a></li>
<li><a href="#clinical-manifestation">Clinical Manifestation</a></li>
<li><a href="#clinically-dormant-stage---latency">Clinically Dormant Stage - Latency</a></li>
<li><a href="#hiv-set-point">HIV set point</a></li>
<li><a href="#time-course">Time Course</a></li>
<li><a href="#opportunistic-infections">Opportunistic Infections</a></li>
<li><a href="#neurological-disease">Neurological Disease</a></li>
<li><a href="#diagnostics">Diagnostics</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#hiv-antiviral-models">HIV Antiviral Models</a><ul>
<li><a href="#binding">Binding</a></li>
<li><a href="#fusion-inhib">Fusion Inhib</a></li>
<li><a href="#nucleoside-analogue-reverse-transcriptase-inhibitors-nrtis">Nucleoside Analogue Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors: NRTIs</a></li>
<li><a href="#non-nucleoside-reverse-transcriptase-inhibitors-nnrtis">non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs)</a></li>
<li><a href="#integrase-inhibitors">Integrase Inhibitors</a></li>
<li><a href="#protease-inhibitors">Protease Inhibitors</a></li>
<li><a href="#highly-active-antiretroviral-therapy-or-haart">Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapy, or HAART</a></li>
<li><a href="#considerations-when-choosing-haart">Considerations When Choosing HAART</a></li>
<li><a href="#treatment-failure">Treatment Failure</a></li>
<li><a href="#immune-reconsitution-syndrome">Immune Reconsitution Syndrome</a></li>
<li><a href="#truvada---prophylaxis">Truvada - Prophylaxis</a></li>
<li><a href="#htlv">HTLV</a><h2 id="family-retroviridae">Family Retroviridae</h2>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Alpha-Epsilonretrovirus and Lentivirus</li>
<li>Lentivirus<ul>
<li>Species: HIV-1 and HIV-2<h3 id="morphology">Morphology</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>A Type: Non-enveloped, immature pareticles. Endogenous and non-infectious.</li>
<li>B Type: Enveloped. Acentric Core</li>
<li>C Type: Central Core</li>
<li>D Type: Central and cylindrical core</li>
<li>Epsilon, Lenti, Spuma all similar to D-Type, but with different core shapes. Lenti is cone shaped, epsi<h3 id="species">Species</h3>
</li>
<li>HIV 1 and 2 share 40% sequence homology</li>
<li>Type 1 predominant form worldwide</li>
<li>Type 2 prevalent onliy in west africa and is lest virulent.</li>
<li>Origin: SImian Immunoeficiency virus (SIV) is a primate retrovirus.<h3 id="structure">Structure</h3>
</li>
<li>RNA+ which <em>can</em> function as mRNA, but with HIV it does not.</li>
<li>Each virion carries 2 identical copes of viral mRNA</li>
<li>Envelope contains both <strong>transmembrane</strong> and <strong>surface</strong> proteins<h3 id="proviral-genome">Proviral Genome</h3>
</li>
<li>GAG - matrix, capsid, nucleosome</li>
<li>POL </li>
<li>ENV</li>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://github.com/BGASM/medNotes/blob/23850cbd41869d2dbb6aa7664824552e90733361/MMG%2Fimg%2Fhivproviral.JPG" data-is-external-image="true"  alt="provirus" /></figure><h3 id="life-cycle">Life Cycle</h3>
</li>
<li>Attachment between gp120 and CD4 followed by interaction with co-receptor CCR5 or CXCR 4</li>
<li>CD4/CCR5 - R5 virus”, initial infection</li>
<li>CD4/CXCR4 “X4 virus”, later in infection</li>
<li>CD4/CXCR4&amp;CCR5 - “X4/R5</li>
<li>Following receptor/co-receptor binding, gp41 mediates fusion of the viral envelope with the cell membrane. After membrane fusion, the nucleocapsid is released into the cytoplasm.</li>
<li>Reverse transcribed into DNA from RNA.<ul>
<li><strong>RT is a very error prone process which results in multiple mutant drug resistant strains</strong></li>
<li>RNA strand in hybrid gets digested by RNaseH</li>
<li>Second DNA strand gets synthesized using the new DNA as a template</li>
<li>Produces a dsDNA known as <strong>proviral DNA</strong></li>
<li>Long-Terminal-Repeat (LTR) formed at each end</li>
<li>Proviral DNA enters nucleus and integrates into cell DNA</li>
<li>Proviral DNA is replicated now along with the host genome every time the host cells divide.</li>
<li>Integrated DNA gets transcribed and translated</li>
<li><strong>Viral promoter and polyadenylation signals</strong> are located in the <strong>LTR</strong></li>
<li>Viral RNA can be used as mRNA or act as knew denomes<ul>
<li>Some are intact genome, some are subgenomic RNA</li>
<li>Some are nucelocapsids</li>
<li>Maturation after budding gives rise to viral<h3 id="transmission">Transmission</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Direct blood contact: transfusions, nbeedles, open wounds</li>
<li>Sexual intercourse</li>
<li>Prinatal transmission<h3 id="pathogenesis">Pathogenesis</h3>
</li>
<li>Virus infect CD4 T cells and macrophages</li>
<li>Also infects dendritic cells</li>
<li><strong>T cells lytically infected</strong></li>
<li><strong>Mphage are persisitently infected and serve as a reservoir</strong></li>
<li>Loss of CD4 over time<h3 id="clinical-manifestation">Clinical Manifestation</h3>
</li>
<li>Primary/Acute HIV (2wk - 3mo)</li>
<li>Initial infection usually due to R5 virus that infects CCR5 cells</li>
<li>Fever, fatigue, rash, headache, swollen lymph nodes, sore throat</li>
<li>Some are asympomatic</li>
<li>Immune system begins to respond by producing <strong>anti-HIV Ab. This process is called sero-conversion.</strong> <ul>
<li>Ab testing before this time may miss the virus. This is a <strong>window period</strong><h3 id="clinically-dormant-stage---latency">Clinically Dormant Stage - Latency</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Can last years without HAART</li>
<li>Asymp</li>
<li><strong>Level of virus in blood decreases and stays at ‘steady state’</strong><h3 id="hiv-set-point">HIV set point</h3>
</li>
<li>Reflects a <strong>stabilized HIV viral load</strong> in a person after acute phase has ended</li>
<li>Higher set point → faster progression to AIDS</li>
<li>Viral Load &gt; 75000 copies/ml and CD$ &lt; 200 ml</li>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://github.com/BGASM/medNotes/blob/23850cbd41869d2dbb6aa7664824552e90733361/MMG%2Fimg%2Fhivtimecourse.JPG" data-is-external-image="true"  alt="HIV Timecourse" /></figure><h3 id="time-course">Time Course</h3>
</li>
<li>Lifelong infection<h3 id="opportunistic-infections">Opportunistic Infections</h3>
</li>
<li>Parasitic</li>
<li>Toxoplasma gondii</li>
<li>Cryptosporidium</li>
<li>Fungal</li>
<li>Candida albicans</li>
<li>Cryptococcus neoformans</li>
<li>Pneumocystis carinii</li>
<li>Histoplasma capsulatum</li>
<li>Viral</li>
<li>CMV</li>
<li>Herpes Zoster and Herpes Simplex</li>
<li>EBV</li>
<li>Bacterial</li>
<li>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</li>
<li>Mycobacterium avium-intracellular complex  </li>
<li>Kaposi Sarcoma HHV-8<ul>
<li>Purple papular lesions all over body</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Non-Hodgkin lymphoma</li>
<li>EBV related lymphoma<h3 id="neurological-disease">Neurological Disease</h3>
</li>
<li>AIDS related Dementia</li>
<li>Virus carried to CNS by monocytes and macrophages</li>
<li>Microglia and astrocytes get infected</li>
<li>Slow deterioration of cognitive function<h3 id="diagnostics">Diagnostics</h3>
</li>
<li>ELISA or Western blot look for presence of p24 (capsid protein)</li>
<li>PCR</li>
<li>RT/PCR</li>
<li>Or assay for Ab to viral proteins by ELISA or Western</li>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://github.com/BGASM/medNotes/blob/23850cbd41869d2dbb6aa7664824552e90733361/MMG%2Fimg%2Fhivlab.JPG" data-is-external-image="true"  alt="HIV Labs" /></figure></li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Combination immunoassay for HIV 1/2</li>
<li>DIfferentiation immunoassay</li>
<li>Nucleic Acid Test<h2 id="hiv-antiviral-models">HIV Antiviral Models</h2>
</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Receptor Blocking</li>
<li>Fusion inhibition</li>
<li>Reverser Transcriptase Inhibitors and Nucleoside Analogues</li>
<li>Protease Inhibitors</li>
<li>Integrase Inhibitors</li>
<li>HAART - Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapy<h3 id="binding">Binding</h3>
</li>
<li>CCR5 blockers</li>
<li>Maraviroc </li>
<li>wont work on CSCR4<h3 id="fusion-inhib">Fusion Inhib</h3>
</li>
<li>T20 Fuzeon/Enfuvirtide</li>
<li>Block HIV ability to bind and fuse the viral envelope with cell membrane</li>
<li>Designed to be used in combo with other.<h3 id="nucleoside-analogue-reverse-transcriptase-inhibitors-nrtis">Nucleoside Analogue Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors: NRTIs</h3>
</li>
<li>AZT thymidine analogue </li>
<li>Since it lacks a 3’ OH group, it serves as a chain terminator, thereby blocking the replication cycle.</li>
<li>Host cell 100 fold less sensitive to AZT than RT<h3 id="non-nucleoside-reverse-transcriptase-inhibitors-nnrtis">non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs)</h3>
</li>
<li>These drugs bind to RT and block its activity so there is no incorporation of nucleotides. Drugs in this class include: Delavridine (Rescriptor)  Nevirapine (Viramune) Efravirenz (Sustiva)<h3 id="integrase-inhibitors">Integrase Inhibitors</h3>
</li>
<li>Block viral integrase<h3 id="protease-inhibitors">Protease Inhibitors</h3>
</li>
<li>Interfere with processing of viral proteins.<h3 id="highly-active-antiretroviral-therapy-or-haart">Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapy, or HAART</h3>
</li>
<li>Because HIV can become resistant to any of the drugs currently in use, combination treatments must be used to effectively suppress the virus.</li>
<li>When multiple drugs (three or more) are used in combination, it is referred to as highly active antiretroviral therapy, or HAART (or just ART).<h3 id="considerations-when-choosing-haart">Considerations When Choosing HAART</h3>
</li>
<li>Use mixture of drugs (typically 3-4) with different mechanisms of action.</li>
<li>Insure no cross-resistance.</li>
<li>Minimize side effects to improve compliance.</li>
<li>Combine drugs into single pill to improve compliance.</li>
<li>Decrease number of times taken per day to improve compliance.</li>
<li>Decide when to initiate therapy.</li>
<li>Conduct genotype and drug resistance testing to guide choice of regimen.<h3 id="treatment-failure">Treatment Failure</h3>
</li>
<li>Signs include Weight loss, anemia, fever, new infections, TB, HSV, CMV</li>
<li>Continued detection of viral PCR</li>
<li>Low CD4 count</li>
<li>Causes could be poor compliance, viral resistence, inadequate drug absorption or suboptimal dosing.<h3 id="immune-reconsitution-syndrome">Immune Reconsitution Syndrome</h3>
</li>
<li>Reported in chronically infected HIV-AIDS patients treated with new anti-retroviral combos</li>
<li>As the immune system begins to recover there is a massive inflammaotry response that makes symptoms worse<h3 id="truvada---prophylaxis">Truvada - Prophylaxis</h3>
</li>
<li>Combines two HIV medicines in one pill and is taken to reduce risk of getting HIV.</li>
<li>Both drugs are <strong>NRTIs</strong> and block reverse transcriptase <h3 id="htlv">HTLV</h3>
</li>
<li>Retrovirus that causes adult <strong>acute T cell lymphocytic leukemia</strong> ATLL</li>
<li>Virus is cell associated: spread via blood transfusion, sexual intercourse, or breast feeding</li>
<li>Infect CD4 t cells</li>
<li>Tax gene product activates cellular genes encoding T cell growth factos like IL2, which may cause tumor formation</li>
<li><strong>Long latent period (30 years) before leukemia</strong></li>
<li>Tumor cells contain proviral DNA</li>
<li>Tumor cells don’t awlays express viral protein</li>
<li>Endemic in parts of Japan</li>
<li>No treatments exist for acute or chronic HTLV</li>
</ul>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Virology V</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-v.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-v.html</id>
            <category term="MMG"/>

        <updated>2020-12-06T17:14:35-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Picornavirus - Rhino,LifecyclePoliovirusCoxsackieviruses: Group A and BRhinovirusesNorovirusesCoronavirusesSARS-COV2Replication:SARS-COVMERS-CoVURTRotavirusPicornavirus - Rhino,Plus Strand, Non-EnvelopedEnterovirusPoliovirusCoxsakievirusEchovirusEnterovirus D68Rhinovirus only one that doesn’t get past the nose/mouthHepatovirusHepatitis AStart in respiratory tract.Travel to target tissue skin, muscle, brain, liverLifecycleBind to cell using viral capsid proteinUpon binding, change in virus structure.RNA+ injected directly to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <ul>
<li><a href="#picornavirus---rhino">Picornavirus - Rhino,</a><ul>
<li><a href="#lifecycle">Lifecycle</a></li>
<li><a href="#poliovirus">Poliovirus</a></li>
<li><a href="#coxsackieviruses-group-a-and-b">Coxsackieviruses: Group A and B</a></li>
<li><a href="#rhinoviruses">Rhinoviruses</a></li>
<li><a href="#noroviruses">Noroviruses</a></li>
<li><a href="#coronaviruses">Coronaviruses</a><ul>
<li><a href="#sars-cov2">SARS-COV2</a></li>
<li><a href="#replication">Replication:</a></li>
<li><a href="#sars-cov">SARS-COV</a></li>
<li><a href="#mers-cov">MERS-CoV</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#urt">URT</a><ul>
<li><a href="#rotavirus">Rotavirus</a><h1 id="picornavirus---rhino">Picornavirus - Rhino,</h1>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Plus Strand, Non-Enveloped</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Enterovirus<ul>
<li>Poliovirus</li>
<li>Coxsakievirus</li>
<li>Echovirus</li>
<li>Enterovirus D68</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Rhinovirus <em>only one that doesn’t get past the nose/mouth</em></li>
<li>Hepatovirus<ul>
<li>Hepatitis A</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Start in respiratory tract.</li>
<li>Travel to target tissue <em>skin, muscle, brain, liver</em><h2 id="lifecycle">Lifecycle</h2>
</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Bind</strong> to cell using <strong>viral capsid protein</strong></li>
<li>Upon binding, change in virus structure.<ul>
<li>RNA+ injected directly to cytoplasm</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Picorn genome has <strong>one large ORF</strong>, that makes a single polyprotein.</li>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://github.com/BGASM/medNotes/blob/23850cbd41869d2dbb6aa7664824552e90733361/MMG%2Fimg%2Fpico.JPG" data-is-external-image="true"  alt="pico genome" /></figure></li>
<li>Several encoded proteins are <strong>Proteases</strong>, that cleave polyprotein into various proteins:<ul>
<li>Capsid proteins</li>
<li><strong>Viral replicase (RDRP)</strong></li>
<li>VPg which bind viral 5’</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>RDRP is used to make complementary RNA+</strong>, which makes more RNA+</li>
<li>New RNA+ used to:<ul>
<li>Make more viral prot</li>
<li>Template to make more -RNA</li>
<li>Package into capsid, make new virion</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Procapsid formed from protomers VP0,1,3. <ul>
<li><em>5 protomers to form pentamer, 12 pentamer to form procapsid.</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Viral Rna inserted into procapsid, <em>VP0 is cleaved into VP2 + VP4</em>, forming mature capsid</li>
<li>Released by cell lysis (<em>cytolytic</em>)<h2 id="poliovirus">Poliovirus</h2>
</li>
<li>Enterovirus</li>
<li>Entry into mouth</li>
<li>Replication in pharynx, GI, lymphatics</li>
<li><em>Hematologic spread to lymphatics</em> -&gt; <strong>CNS Invasion</strong></li>
<li>Viral spread along nerve fibers</li>
<li><strong>Destruction of motor neurons</strong></li>
<li>Salk Vaccine: Inactivated</li>
<li>Sabin Vaccine: Live<h2 id="coxsackieviruses-group-a-and-b">Coxsackieviruses: Group A and B</h2>
</li>
<li>Infants and children</li>
<li>Fecal-oral tx</li>
<li>Herpangina (mouth blisters) caused by A:</li>
<li>Hand, Foot, Mouth commonly caused by Cox A16</li>
<li>Cox B:<ul>
<li>Myocarditis</li>
<li>Pleurodynia</li>
<li>Cox Asecepitc Meningitis<h2 id="rhinoviruses">Rhinoviruses</h2>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Unable to replicate in Gi (labile to pH)</li>
<li>Common cause of URT infection</li>
<li>Tx as aerosole and on fomite</li>
<li>Asymptomatic in many case<h2 id="noroviruses">Noroviruses</h2>
</li>
<li>Member of calicivirus</li>
<li>Oral-fecal tx</li>
<li>Resistant to heat, pH, detergent</li>
<li>Food-borne, Direct contact</li>
<li>Commonly outbreaks in long-term care facilities</li>
<li>No specific treatment. Prevent dehydration</li>
<li>Diagnosis:<ul>
<li>Real time RT/PCR</li>
<li>EIA (enzyme immunoassay) for outbreaks. Not specific enough for individual cases<h2 id="coronaviruses">Coronaviruses</h2>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Nidovirales &gt; Coronaviridae &gt; Coronavirinae &gt; Beta coronavirus &gt; SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, SARS-COV2<h3 id="sars-cov2">SARS-COV2</h3>
</li>
<li>RNA+, 30 kb</li>
<li>Structural proteins:  S, E, M, N</li>
<li>Several viral enzymes</li>
<li>Enveloped virion 80-100 nm</li>
<li>Envelope contains club-shaped glycoprotein projects that appear crown-like.</li>
<li><strong>S protein</strong>:<ul>
<li>Attaches to host ACE2 receptor using two subunits, S1 and S2</li>
<li>S1 determines host range and cellular tropism by RBD</li>
<li>S2 mediates virus-cell membrane fusion by HR1 and HR2</li>
<li>Animals were intermediate host, no ACE2 binding in non-humans</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>M protein</strong><ul>
<li>Responsible for transmembrane transport of nutrients, bud relase, and envelope formation</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>N E protein</strong>:<ul>
<li>Interfere with host immune response</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Host Factors:<ul>
<li><strong>hACE2</strong></li>
<li>Elderly more susceptible</li>
<li><em>CPE</em> Cytopathic effect and cytokine storm.<h3 id="replication">Replication:</h3>
</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Spike binds ACE2 receptor. Remove envelope</li>
<li>Translate ORF1a/b</li>
<li>Cleave proteins. Repl/Transcriptionm complex use RNA+ as templat</li>
<li>RNA+ produced through replication, becomes genome for baby virus</li>
<li>NESTED RNA from step 4 translated into S E M N proteins, make viral particle</li>
<li>Spike, envelope and membrane enter ER and nucleocapsid protein combine dwith RNA+ genomic RNA. Merge into complete virus in ER-Golgi and get excreted.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://github.com/BGASM/medNotes/blob/23850cbd41869d2dbb6aa7664824552e90733361/MMG%2Fimg%2Fsars.JPG" data-is-external-image="true"  alt="SARS COV" /></figure></li>
<li>Seven human coronaviruses, some common ones:<ul>
<li>229E (alpha)</li>
<li>NL63 (alpha)</li>
<li>OC43 (beta)</li>
<li>HKU1 (beta)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Common cause of URT infect in adult.</li>
<li>Second most common cause of ‘cold’, right behind rhinovirus.</li>
<li>Occasionally cause enteric infect.</li>
<li>Rarely cause neuroligcial</li>
<li>Sometimes cornavirus that infect animals evolve and become human coronavirus:<ul>
<li>MERS-CoV</li>
<li>SARS-CoV</li>
<li>SARS-CoV-2<h3 id="sars-cov">SARS-COV</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>person-person tx</li>
<li>most virulent during 2nd week of illness, peak of respiratory excretion</li>
<li>MOst case of human-human occur in health care setting</li>
<li>Symptoms:<ul>
<li>influenza-like</li>
<li>fever, malaise, myalgia, headache, diarrhea, shivereing</li>
<li>Cough, SoB, diarrhea in first/second week</li>
<li>sever case evolve rapidly, progress to respiratory distress -&gt; ICU<h3 id="mers-cov">MERS-CoV</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="urt">URT</h2>
<ul>
<li>Causes: 90% due to viruses, 10% Bacteria</li>
<li>The common cold: runny nose, sore throat, sneezing, “bronchitis”, coughing, headaches, body aches, low grade fever.</li>
<li>Over 200 viruses in many different families can cause upper respiratory infections;</li>
<li>Rhinovirus (Picornaviridae)*</li>
<li>Coronavirus (Coronaviridae)*</li>
<li>Adenovirus (Adenoviridae)*</li>
<li>RSV (Paramyxoviridae)</li>
<li>Parainfluenza (Paramyxoviridae)</li>
<li>Influenza (Orthomyxoviridae)<h3 id="rotavirus">Rotavirus</h3>
<ul>
<li>Respiratory, Enteric, Orphan</li>
<li>Group A-E. Group A most common cause of childhood diarrhea and dastroenteritis</li>
<li>Non-eveloped, double layer capsid</li>
<li>Survive gGI</li>
<li>50% hospitalization in children with diarrhea during autom winter spring</li>
<li>NSP4 protein has toxin-like activity</li>
<li>Two vaccine (live, oral)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Virology III</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-iii.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-iii.html</id>
            <category term="MMG"/>

        <updated>2020-12-06T17:14:17-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Small/Medium DNA virusesPolyoma, Papilloma, AdenoAdenoReplicationParvoPapillomaPolyomavirusMerkel Cell Virus MCVSmall/Medium DNA virusesPolyoma, Papilloma, AdenoAdenoTwo genera, aviadenovirus and mastasdenovirusGenome is ds Linear DNA 30-40kb long5’ terminal protein and DNA binding proteinCapsid icsosahedron with fiber attachment protein at each verticeNON-EnvelopedCan utilize both strands for transcription. Makes a lot of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <ul>
<li><a href="#smallmedium-dna-viruses">Small/Medium DNA viruses</a><ul>
<li><a href="#polyoma-papilloma-adeno">Polyoma, Papilloma, Adeno</a><ul>
<li><a href="#adeno">Adeno</a><ul>
<li><a href="#replication">Replication</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#parvo">Parvo</a></li>
<li><a href="#papilloma">Papilloma</a><ul>
<li><a href="#polyomavirus">Polyomavirus</a><ul>
<li><a href="#merkel-cell-virus-mcv">Merkel Cell Virus MCV</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="smallmedium-dna-viruses">Small/Medium DNA viruses</h2>
<h3 id="polyoma-papilloma-adeno">Polyoma, Papilloma, Adeno</h3>
<h4 id="adeno">Adeno</h4>
<p>Two genera, aviadenovirus and mastasdenovirus
Genome is ds Linear DNA 30-40kb long
5’ terminal protein and DNA binding protein
Capsid icsosahedron with fiber attachment protein at each vertice
NON-Enveloped
Can utilize both strands for transcription. 
Makes a lot of dsRNA which also <strong>induces a ton of IFN</strong></p>
<h5 id="replication">Replication</h5>
<p>Enter cells via receptor mediated endocytosis
Early genes transcibed and translated useing host protein</p>
<ul>
<li>Activate more viral gene expression</li>
<li>Induce host enter S phase</li>
<li>Block apoptosis</li>
<li>Inhibit IFN</li>
<li>In permissive: early gene expression followed by viral DNA replication - using 5’ terminal protein as primer</li>
<li>DNA replication followed by expression of <strong>late genes</strong><ul>
<li>Structural proteins that get made in cytosol and then target back into nucleus</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>High copy number leads to cell lysis</li>
<li>Can establish latent or persistent infect in some cells.</li>
</ul>
<p>47 serotype divided into 6 subgroups (A-F)
Cause respiratory disease, conjunctivitis, hemorrhagic cystitis, and gastroenteritis.
Differences due to penton base and fiber protein
Establish lytic infection in respiratory and GI tract. Latent in lymphoid tissue
Cause URI and croup
Immunocompromised leads to fulminant respiratory failure, hepatitis, death</p>
<p>Virus enter URT through eyes or upper resp. Goes LRT or GI then into lymph nodes. Skin or other ogans, and then resolves or persists.
One week incubateion and then contagious</p>
<p>Acute respiratory disease: 3,4,7,14
Hemorrhagic Cystitits: 11, 21</p>
<p>Treatment:
No specific anti-viral drugs, some broad specturm work for immunocompromised.
Vaccine made for military a while ago, but production stopped.</p>
<p>#####</p>
<h4 id="parvo">Parvo</h4>
<p>Smallest DNA virus
Non-enveloped icosahedral capsid 18-26nm
Genome is ssDNA, 5.5kb
Genus ertyhrovirus, species B19
Depndovirus, species adeno associated virus - species requries adenovirus present to infect
Only able to infect proliferating cells.</p>
<ul>
<li>Dependednt on cellular enzymes, cannot induce quiescent cells into cell cycle</li>
</ul>
<p>Genome:
Inverted repeats at the ends of genome
Partially uncoated, need to get viral dn into nucleus to make dsDNA
Make mRNA to make viral proteins
Single stranded dna can be + or -</p>
<p>Fifth classic childhood rash and can infect dogs</p>
<p>Primary replication in respiratory tract, then bone marrow -&gt; kills replicating erythroid precursor cells
Virema
Complexes precipitate in skin and joints, causing rash
Rash on both cheeks, followed with erythematous rash on trunk nad limbs
No specific thrrapy or vaccine</p>
<p>Aplastic Crisis
Replicates in RBC precursors
PT with Chronic hemolytic anemia -&gt; aplastic anema can occur
Virus can cross placenta and cause hydrops fetalis</p>
<h4 id="papilloma">Papilloma</h4>
<p>Small, non-enveloped
dsCircular DNA
Depened on host cell polymerase to express their genes
100 serotypes
Some sexually transmitted
16 and 18 cause squamous cell carcinoma
Lytic replication in permissive cells
Can persist either integrated or unintegrated
Warts: Benign - Plantar/common - transmitted by direct contact
Laryngeal papillomatosis - benign tumors on larynx</p>
<p>Development of papilloma (warts)</p>
<p>HPV and cancer:
85% cervical carcinoma contain HPV dna
HPV genome is episomal (not integrated into the host genome) in cervical warts and pre-neoplastic lesions
Genome is integrated into genome of malignant cervical cancers
Can also cause cancer in vagina and vulva, penis, anus, and throat.</p>
<p>How does virus cause tumor?
E5 gene - activate epidermal growth factor (EGF) receptor
E6 gene - Targets p53 suppressor for degrade
E7 gene - Inhibits pRb suppressor from halting cell cycle</p>
<p><strong>5 promotes growth, 6 and 7 prevent suppression</strong></p>
<p>Detection:
Papanicolaou stain (pap smear)
Detects perinuclear vacuolated cytoplasm, sign of cancer and of HPV
PCR</p>
<p>Prevention:
Gardasil for male and female
Gardasil protect against HPV 6,11,16,18 (cervical and anal cancer, cervical warts)
Gardasil 9 also protects against 31,33,45,52,58
16,18 cause 80% of cervical cancer
6,11 cause 90% genital warts
Cervarix only for female
Cervarix: protect only against 16,18</p>
<h5 id="polyomavirus">Polyomavirus</h5>
<p>Small non-enveloped
Circular dsDNA
Two human viruses BK and JC
Don’t usually cause disease in healhty people, but they can establish latent infection in kidneys
In immunocompromised the virus can reactivate and cause severe urinary tract infections (BK)
or Viremia and CNS infection with progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML JC)
Inoculate into respiratory tract
replicate and cause primary viremia
Multiply in kidney
Secondary viremia, healthy people either resolve or go latent
Immunosuppressed see reactivation and then urinary tract if BK, CNS if JC</p>
<h6 id="merkel-cell-virus-mcv">Merkel Cell Virus MCV</h6>
<p>ds DNA, a polyoma virus
Infect older kids and adults
Integration of MCV genome is cause of rate but aggressive skin cancer
80% merkel cell carcinomas contain MCV genome
1500 caseas/year
High incidence in elderly</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Virology II</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-ii.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-ii.html</id>
            <category term="MMG"/>

        <updated>2020-12-06T17:14:01-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Pathways of entery and the stages of viral infection in humansStagesGeneral Characteristics of Viral infectionMechanisms of Viral PathogenesisHost Defense: InnateHumoral Immunity:Cellular Immunity:Viral Evasion:Immunization:Attenuated Live Viral Vadccines:Killed (Inactivated) Viral VaccineSubunit Vaccine:Recombinant Viral VaccineVaccine Limitations:Anti-Viral DrugsPathways of entery and the stages of viral infection in humansViral life&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <ul>
<li><a href="#pathways-of-entery-and-the-stages-of-viral-infection-in-humans">Pathways of entery and the stages of viral infection in humans</a><ul>
<li><a href="#stages">Stages</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#general-characteristics-of-viral-infection">General Characteristics of Viral infection</a></li>
<li><a href="#mechanisms-of-viral-pathogenesis">Mechanisms of Viral Pathogenesis</a><ul>
<li><a href="#host-defense-innate">Host Defense: Innate</a></li>
<li><a href="#humoral-immunity">Humoral Immunity:</a></li>
<li><a href="#cellular-immunity">Cellular Immunity:</a></li>
<li><a href="#viral-evasion">Viral Evasion:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#immunization">Immunization:</a><ul>
<li><a href="#attenuated-live-viral-vadccines">Attenuated Live Viral Vadccines:</a></li>
<li><a href="#killed-inactivated-viral-vaccine">Killed (Inactivated) Viral Vaccine</a></li>
<li><a href="#subunit-vaccine">Subunit Vaccine:</a></li>
<li><a href="#recombinant-viral-vaccine">Recombinant Viral Vaccine</a></li>
<li><a href="#vaccine-limitations">Vaccine Limitations:</a></li>
<li><a href="#anti-viral-drugs">Anti-Viral Drugs</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pathways-of-entery-and-the-stages-of-viral-infection-in-humans">Pathways of entery and the stages of viral infection in humans</h2>
<p>Viral life cycle
Tropism
Acute vs Chronic
And pathogenicity</p>
<p>Learning about interferon in antiviral defense
Humoral and cellular immunity
Vaccination and antiviral drugs
Methods for detection and Diagnosis</p>
<p>Pathways:
Respiratory, alimentary, urogenital, lesions, conjuctiva, direct blood, bites, arthropod bites</p>
<p>Enveloped viruses in general are more sensitive to dessication, pH, detergent  AND require direct contact via blood, aerosols.
Non-enveloped in general are more resistant.
e.g. ENterovirus can withstand acid environment of the stomach</p>
<h3 id="stages">Stages</h3>
<p>Entry
Initiation of infect at primary site
Activation of protection/immunity
REplication at primary site
Some virus replicate in secondary target organ
Infection of final target tissue
Host responses that can limit or contribute (immunopathogenesis)
Release/shedding of virus
Resolution of infectior or persistent infection</p>
<h2 id="general-characteristics-of-viral-infection">General Characteristics of Viral infection</h2>
<p>Infection is cell type and species specific
Types of cells taht can be infected == tissue tropism of virus
Determinants of tropism == receptors, enzymes, environmnet
Cells that a virus can reproduce in == Permissive
Infection of cells can lead to <strong>abortive infection</strong>
Successfully infected cells can be lytic or non-lytic
Lytic leads to cell death
Non-lytic can produce virus == budding
Non-lytic can be dormant.
Both styles of non-lytic are considered <strong>peristently infected</strong>
Temporary infection == acute
Persistent == chronic
Persistent can lead to constent shedding OR the virus may be latenet. If latent, can see NO free virus, but still infected.</p>
<h2 id="mechanisms-of-viral-pathogenesis">Mechanisms of Viral Pathogenesis</h2>
<p>Direct killing == lysis, inhib protein synth, altered membrane/function
Direct infect of immune cells == immunodef
Indirect effects on immune system
Immunopathology == inflamm, fever, edema, vascular permeability
Oncogenic transformation == virus can express oncogenes and cause cancer</p>
<h3 id="host-defense-innate">Host Defense: Innate</h3>
<p>Cytokines
Interferon Alpha/Beta important agianst viral infect
Virally infected cells induced to make IFN A or B
DS RNA is a signal to induce IFN synth
IFN binds to receptors on infect and uninfect cells
Binding IFN results in antiviral state
If infect, antiviral state activated to interrupt viral life cycle
Other cells are now primed to defend against infect.</p>
<ul>
<li>PKR is a kinase activated by DS RNA or by IFN<ul>
<li>Activated PKR phosphorylates eIF2a translation which inhibits tranlsation and leads to block of both viral and host protein synthesis</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>RNase L also induced by IFN.</li>
<li>Needs oligo A to activate</li>
<li>Oligo A induced by IFN and activated by DS RNA<ul>
<li>Degrades viral and cellular RNA</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>RNaseL and PKR inhibit viral replication
Summary:</li>
</ul>
<p>** PKR and OLIGOA synthesized in inactive form in response to IFN. Both enzymes activated if DS RNA, which happens during viral infect**</p>
<h3 id="humoral-immunity">Humoral Immunity:</h3>
<p>Effective agianst extracellular stage
Neutralizing antibodies prevent virus from enter or replicating in cells.</p>
<ul>
<li>Block attachment, penetration, membrane fusion, or uncoating
Ab coating viruses can induce opsonization
Enveloped virus coated in Ab can be lysed by complement
Virally infeccted cells can be lysed by commplement, or NK cells using ADCC (antibody dependent cellular cytotoxicity)
Limits: Not as effective in late infect
Ab alone not sufficient to confer long term immunity</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="cellular-immunity">Cellular Immunity:</h3>
<p>Tcells recognize forein ag on mhc i or ii
When cells are infected, new foreign viral proteins get boudn to mhc i and presented
Activation requires 2 signals: Ag binding and CD4 activation</p>
<h3 id="viral-evasion">Viral Evasion:</h3>
<p>Rapid acute infection, adaptive doesnt have time
Ag variation
Restricted or no expression of viral gene products
Active suppression of MHC1
Infect cells that do not normally express MHCi
Decrease cell adhesion molecule so T cell cannot bind and interact
Kill or suppress immune cells</p>
<h2 id="immunization">Immunization:</h2>
<p>Neutralizing Ab block early stages
Subsequent infect elicit stronger secondary immune response
Break infection-spread cycle</p>
<h3 id="attenuated-live-viral-vadccines">Attenuated Live Viral Vadccines:</h3>
<p>Use related nbut non-pathogenic version of virus
Or attneuated strains of virus
Stimulate both humoral and cellular immune system and confer long term immunit
Sometimes even attenuated can cause disease
Can revert to virulence</p>
<h3 id="killed-inactivated-viral-vaccine">Killed (Inactivated) Viral Vaccine</h3>
<p>Virus inactivated by chemical or physical without destroying antigenicity
Require adjuvants and multiple dose
Inefficient for immune response and long term immunity
Safe</p>
<h3 id="subunit-vaccine">Subunit Vaccine:</h3>
<p>Purified viral proteins used as immunogen
Involkves cloning the gene of interest in a vector and using heterologus cell to produce the protein</p>
<h3 id="recombinant-viral-vaccine">Recombinant Viral Vaccine</h3>
<p>Gene encoding a viral antigen that is target of neutralizing Ab is cloned into a non-virulent viral vector</p>
<p>DNA/RNA Base vaccine</p>
<h3 id="vaccine-limitations">Vaccine Limitations:</h3>
<p>– Attenuated strains may be difficult to develop.
– Inactivation may destroy antigenicity.
– Purified proteins may not be immunogenic.
– Virus may “mutate” or evolve too rapidly.</p>
<h3 id="anti-viral-drugs">Anti-Viral Drugs</h3>
<p>Identify drugs that inhibti viral replication without harming human host
Targetr any stage of viral life cycle</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Virology I</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-i.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/virology-i.html</id>
            <category term="MMG"/>

        <updated>2020-12-06T17:13:41-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Overall GoalsDefinitionsClassificationRNACapsidReceptor Mediated EndocytosisOther Surface EntryUncoating and TargettingReplication/Gene StrategiesGene Expression/Replication of DNA VirusesOverall GoalsUnderstand fundamenta l structure, classification and replication cycle of virusesUnderstand biologya and PathogenesisUnderstand host-defense strategiesHow virus undermine these defensesHow medications can interfereDefinitionsInfectiousObligate intracellularLack a metabolismSubmicroscopic - 25nm-000’sn,FilterableNo division for replication.ClassificationMorphology - Size,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <ul>
<li><a href="#overall-goals">Overall Goals</a><ul>
<li><a href="#definitions">Definitions</a></li>
<li><a href="#classification">Classification</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#rna">RNA</a></li>
<li><a href="#capsid">Capsid</a></li>
<li><a href="#receptor-mediated-endocytosis">Receptor Mediated Endocytosis</a></li>
<li><a href="#other-surface-entry">Other Surface Entry</a></li>
<li><a href="#uncoating-and-targetting">Uncoating and Targetting</a></li>
<li><a href="#replicationgene-strategies">Replication/Gene Strategies</a></li>
<li><a href="#gene-expressionreplication-of-dna-viruses">Gene Expression/Replication of DNA Viruses</a><h2 id="overall-goals">Overall Goals</h2>
</li>
<li>Understand fundamenta l structure, classification and replication cycle of viruses</li>
<li>Understand biologya and PathogenesisUnderstand host-defense strategies</li>
<li>How virus undermine these defenses</li>
<li>How medications can interfere<h3 id="definitions">Definitions</h3>
</li>
<li>Infectious</li>
<li>Obligate intracellular</li>
<li>Lack a metabolism</li>
<li>Submicroscopic - 25nm-000’sn,</li>
<li>Filterable</li>
<li>No division for replication.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="classification">Classification</h3>
<ul>
<li>Morphology - Size, shape, envelope</li>
<li>Genome size, RNA/DNA, +- strand</li>
<li>Proteins</li>
<li>Genome organization and replication strategy</li>
<li>Antigenic properties and serological relations</li>
<li>Biological properties and structural</li>
</ul>
<p>Virus Structure Summary
ALl </p>
<ul>
<li>Viral Genome DNA Structure</li>
<li>Range in size from 5-200 kb</li>
<li>Linear or circular structure</li>
<li>Double or single stranded</li>
<li>Can have unusual structure, such as a Gapped Circle</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="rna">RNA</h2>
<ul>
<li>Double stranded Linear</li>
<li>SIngle stranded LinearPositive sense +<ul>
<li>5-3 directly translated )genome is like mRNA)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Negative Sense or - strand is<ul>
<li>Ambisense: RNA that is in part of positive and in part of negative polarity</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>RNA can have segmented genomes</li>
<li>Circular single stranded RNA are found in the viroids and the hepatitis delta virus HDV</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="capsid">Capsid</h2>
<ul>
<li>Usually one of two repeated structures:<ul>
<li>Helix</li>
<li>Icosahedron</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Composed of structural subunits called protomers</li>
<li>Morphological units are called capsomers, these cluster around an axis of symmetry.</li>
<li>May also have spikes that project from the surgace</li>
<li><strong>Protomers are the structural units, capsomers are the functional units</strong><pre><code>
</code></pre></li>
</ul>
<pre><code>BATHROOM BREAKDOWN</code></pre><pre><code>The account is in the name July 52 Chandler LLC at Michigan State University Federal Credit Union. The account number is 022552282 and the routing number is 272479663.

Virus Attachment to Host

## Receptor Mediated Endocytosis
- Virus binds to receptor at cell surface in areas called coated patients
- Pinches off and forms a coated vesicles
- Endsome can then fuse with others
- Acidification
## Other Surface Entry
- Membrane fusion (enveloped) or pore/channel formation (non-enveloped)
- Receptor 

## Uncoating and Targetting
- Can be partial or complet
- Some viruses, including most DNA virus, must be targeted

## Replication/Gene Strategies
- Class I - VI
- VII: Double stranded DNA with an RNA intermediate (Hepatitis B Virus)

## Gene Expression/Replication of DNA Viruses







--------------------------------
Describe Pathways of entry, and the stages of viral infection.
</code></pre>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Adrenergic_Cholinergic V</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/adrenergic_cholinergic-v.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/adrenergic_cholinergic-v.html</id>
            <category term="Pharm"/>

        <updated>2020-12-06T17:04:23-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    IntroCholinomimeticsDIRECT Cholinomimetic: Agonists on muscarinic and nicotinic receptorsMuscarinic AgonistNicotinic Agonist:Indirect Cholinomimetic: AChE inhibitorsReversible and thereapeuticOrganophosphates - Irreversible, toxicTOXICITY MANIFESTATION AFTER ORGANOPHOSPHATES (OPs) EXPOSURE:CholinolyticsIndirectDirectMuscarinic Anatgonists:Nicotinic Antagonists: NMJ blocksTextbook NotesIntroAceytlchole binds on both Nicotinic and Muscarinic receptorsOn nictotinic it has an ionotropric effect, allowing passage of ions.On&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <ul>
<li><a href="#intro">Intro</a><ul>
<li><a href="#"></a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#cholinomimetics">Cholinomimetics</a><ul>
<li><a href="#direct-cholinomimetic-agonists-on-muscarinic-and-nicotinic-receptors">DIRECT Cholinomimetic: Agonists on muscarinic and nicotinic receptors</a><ul>
<li><a href="#muscarinic-agonist">Muscarinic Agonist</a></li>
<li><a href="#nicotinic-agonist">Nicotinic Agonist:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#indirect-cholinomimetic-ache-inhibitors">Indirect Cholinomimetic: AChE inhibitors</a><ul>
<li><a href="#reversible-and-thereapeutic">Reversible and thereapeutic</a></li>
<li><a href="#organophosphates---irreversible-toxic">Organophosphates - Irreversible, toxic</a></li>
<li><a href="#toxicity-manifestation-after-organophosphates-ops-exposure">TOXICITY MANIFESTATION AFTER ORGANOPHOSPHATES (OPs) EXPOSURE:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#cholinolytics">Cholinolytics</a><ul>
<li><a href="#indirect">Indirect</a></li>
<li><a href="#direct">Direct</a><ul>
<li><a href="#muscarinic-anatgonists">Muscarinic Anatgonists:</a></li>
<li><a href="#nicotinic-antagonists-nmj-blocks">Nicotinic Antagonists: NMJ blocks</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#textbook-notes">Textbook Notes</a><h2 id="intro">Intro</h2>
<h3 id=""></h3>
</li>
<li>Aceytlchole binds on both Nicotinic and Muscarinic receptors</li>
<li>On nictotinic it has an ionotropric effect, allowing passage of ions.</li>
<li>On muscarinic it binds to M receptors and has a metabotropic effect, which are all GPCRs</li>
<li>In PNS it is the parasympathetic system that uses Ach for post-ganglion signalling on muscarinic receptors</li>
<li>CNS<ul>
<li>Nictonic Effects: Reward, arousal, improve task performance</li>
<li>Muscarinic: Learning and memory
Drugs acting on chilinergic systems in the PNS or CNS can act as either cholinomimetics, or cholinolytics.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="cholinomimetics">Cholinomimetics</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Stimulate the cholinergic systems by enhancing the effects of either nicotinic or muscarinic receptors.</p>
</li>
<li><p>THey may also be indirectly stimulated by blocking AchE.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Directy agonists such as nicotine, Ach, carbachol, succinychole, or varenicline</p>
</li>
<li><p>Directly agonist such as pilocarpine and muscarine, ACh, Carbachol, Bethanechol, Methacholine, Cevimeline</p>
<h3 id="direct-cholinomimetic-agonists-on-muscarinic-and-nicotinic-receptors">DIRECT Cholinomimetic: Agonists on muscarinic and nicotinic receptors</h3>
<h4 id="muscarinic-agonist">Muscarinic Agonist</h4>
</li>
<li><p>Esters:</p>
<ul>
<li>Poorly absorveb and little CNS access because they are hydrophilic</li>
<li>They are hydrolyzed in the GI in the following priority:<ul>
<li>ACH &gt;&gt;&gt; METHacholine &gt;&gt;&gt; Bethanechol &gt;&gt;&gt; Carbachol </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ACh use is limited to some opthalmic procedures to cause miosis.</li>
<li>Carbachol has the longest duration<ul>
<li>Better choice drug for causing miosis</li>
<li>Constricts pupil and lowers IOP</li>
<li>Topical and intraoculare injections</li>
<li>AE: May cause asthma if it reaches PNS</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Bethanechol<ul>
<li>Selectivelty stimulates urinary and GI tract</li>
<li>Does not cause bradycardia</li>
<li><strong>Stimulate urinary retention</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Methacholine<ul>
<li>Used for diagnostic only</li>
<li>Not used clinically</li>
<li>Asthma challenge test - bronchoprovocation test</li>
<li>Administer via inhlation</li>
<li>AE: Cardiac arrest</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Alkaloids:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pilocarpine:<ul>
<li>Well absorbed</li>
<li>High affinity to mascarinic receptors: CNS and Periphery</li>
<li>Stimulates tears, sweating, saliva, pupil constriction, and contraction of ciliary muscle</li>
<li>TI: <strong>Glaucoma</strong> decrease IOP via topical or intraocular or dry mouth</li>
<li><strong>AE: Diaphoresis if it reaches systemic circulation</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Synthetics: </p>
<ul>
<li>CEVIMELINE (synthetic):<ul>
<li>Selectivity as M1 and M3 agonist.</li>
<li>Therapeutic uses: - <strong>Treat xerostomia (dry mouth)</strong>. It is a <strong>sialagogue</strong>.<h4 id="nicotinic-agonist">Nicotinic Agonist:</h4>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Esters:</p>
<ul>
<li>ACh</li>
<li>Carbachol</li>
<li>Succinylcholine</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Alkaloids</p>
<ul>
<li>Nicotine:<ul>
<li>Only nicotinic stimulation: CNS and PNS</li>
<li>At a high dose it acts as a blocker. <strong>Desensitization</strong></li>
<li>Higher affinity for neuronal receptors than other tissue</li>
<li>CNS Stimulant: Increase respiratory rate, tremor, convulsions, vomiting</li>
<li>Parenteral Admin: Increase BP, nausea, diarrhea, bladder voiding<ul>
<li>TI: Nicotine Replacement therapy</li>
<li>AE: Increased salivation, upset stomach, bleeding gums, throat irritation</li>
<li>Symptoms of acute nicotine severe poisoning</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Nausea, salivatition, abdominal pain, vomiting, diarrhea, cold sweat, headache, dizziness, confusion, muscle weakness</li>
<li>Hypotension and rapid pulse</li>
<li>Labored breathing</li>
<li>Convulsions</li>
<li>Death from respiratory arrest </li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Synthetics:</p>
<ul>
<li>Varenicline<ul>
<li>Cross BBB</li>
<li>Partial agonist on nicotinic receptors in brain</li>
<li>TI: Smoking cessation</li>
<li>AE: Sleep disturbance and depression<h3 id="indirect-cholinomimetic-ache-inhibitors">Indirect Cholinomimetic: AChE inhibitors</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Increased amount of ACh to act in muscarinic and nicotinic receptors.</p>
</li>
<li><p>CNS: Enhance cholinergic function. High concentrations cause convulsions.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Respiratory, GI, urinary tracts, and eye</strong>: Same as direct-acting cholinomimetics.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Cardiovascular system</strong>: <strong>M2</strong> Inhibitory effect on heart predominates. Little effect on vasculature. </p>
<ul>
<li>Moderate doses – increase vascular resistance and BP.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>NMJ: Increase the strength of contraction, which may cause fasciculation and fibrillations and blockage.</p>
<h4 id="reversible-and-thereapeutic">Reversible and thereapeutic</h4>
</li>
<li><p>Neostigmine and Pyridostigmine: Reversible</p>
<ul>
<li>Low lipid solube so poort absorption</li>
<li>TI: Reverse effects of competititve NMJ blockers (<strong>non-depolarizing muscle releaxant</strong>)</li>
<li>Note, neostigmine also directly activates nicotinic receptors</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Physostigmine: Reversible</p>
<ul>
<li>Highly abosrbed by all routes</li>
<li>Access to CNS</li>
<li>TI: Glaucoma and reversing anticholinergic poisoning (like from atropine)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><strong>NEOSTIGMINE, PYRIDOSTIGMINE, and PHYSOSTIGMINE</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Myasthenia gravis (dec progression symptoms) Diagnosis of myasthenia gravis.</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Donepezil, Galantamine, Rivastigmine: Reversible</p>
<ul>
<li>CNS action</li>
<li>TI: Alzeheimers Disease</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="organophosphates---irreversible-toxic">Organophosphates - Irreversible, toxic</h4>
<ul>
<li>Parathion, Malathion (insecticides), Soman (gas), Sarin (liquid/evaporate as gas)<ul>
<li>Well absorbed from skin, lung, gut, conjunctiva</li>
<li>Lipid soluble: access to CNS.</li>
<li>Mechanism of Toxicity: Hydrolyzed by AChE, but the resulting phosphorylated enzyme.</li>
<li>form a very stable complex with the enzyme</li>
<li>bind to AChE irreversibly. </li>
<li>Require synthesis of the new enzyme to restore its function.</li>
<li>Malathion, parathion must be metabolized to be activated:</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Malathion: Moderately toxic (rapidly metabolized by other pathways to inactive forms in birds and mammals but not insects);</li>
<li>Parathion: Highly Toxic (not detoxified by vertebrates).<h4 id="toxicity-manifestation-after-organophosphates-ops-exposure">TOXICITY MANIFESTATION AFTER ORGANOPHOSPHATES (OPs) EXPOSURE:</h4>
</li>
<li>Acute (min- 24 h): effects include actions on CNS (anxiety, respiratory depression, convulsion)</li>
<li>Initial treatment will be atropine</li>
<li>Muscarinic symptoms: <strong>D U M B B EE L L S</strong>:<ul>
<li><strong>Diarrhea</strong></li>
<li>Urination</li>
<li><strong>Miosis</strong></li>
<li><strong>Bronchoconstriction</strong></li>
<li>Bradycardia</li>
<li>Excitation/Emesis</li>
<li>Lacrimation</li>
<li>Lethargy</li>
<li>Salivation</li>
<li><strong>Sweating</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Nicitonic Symptoms: Mon, Tues, Wed, tHurs, Fri<ul>
<li>Mydriasis</li>
<li>Tachycardia</li>
<li>Weakness</li>
<li>Hypertension</li>
<li>Fasciculations</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Delayed (24h - 2 weeks) and later-onset: nicotinic, muscarinic actions and stronger CNS impairment (encephalopathy, extrapyramidal symptoms, coma).</li>
<li>Atropine has an issue, it only has antimuscarininc effects.</li>
<li>ANTIDOTE to AChEi INTOXICATION (OP): Oxime agents</li>
<li>Pralidoxime:<ul>
<li>Cholinesterase regenerator if given before aging occurs (48-hours).</li>
<li>Works at NMJ but does not prevent CNS effects.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="cholinolytics">Cholinolytics</h2>
<h3 id="indirect">Indirect</h3>
<ul>
<li>Botulinum Toxin:<ul>
<li>Cleave protein associated with fusion and exocytosis of vesicles carrying ACh (<strong>SNARE proteins</strong>)</li>
<li>Prevent docking and release of ACh</li>
<li>TI: Prevent sustained involuntary muscle spasms</li>
<li>Bleopharospasm (excessive blinking)</li>
<li>Severe axillary hyperhidrosis (excessive sweating)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="direct">Direct</h3>
<h4 id="muscarinic-anatgonists">Muscarinic Anatgonists:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Tropicamide: Causes <strong>mydriasis and cycloplegia</strong> good for use in eyes because short acting.</li>
<li>Tiotropium, Ipratropium: <strong>Inhaled</strong>, does not cross BBB. Mostly M3, bronchodilation, - <strong>Asthma and COPD</strong></li>
<li>Atropine: <strong>Reverse bradycardia</strong>, cholinergic poisoning, hyperhidrosis <strong>Dose Dependent</strong>, can also be used in the eyes</li>
<li>Atropine, Scopolamine: Inhibit <strong>excessive salivation and mucus secretion during surgery</strong></li>
<li>Scopolamine: motion sickness</li>
<li>Solifenacin, Tolterodine, Oxybutynin: Urinary bladder spasm/incontinence M1 and M3 affinity -&gt; <strong>OAB</strong></li>
<li><strong>Desloratadine and Diphenhydramine</strong> - Antihistamine drugs with additional muscarinic antagonists mech.</li>
<li>Antimuscarinic Syndrome:<ul>
<li>Red as a beet - skin flushed</li>
<li>Hot as a hare - Hyperthermia</li>
<li>Dry as a bone - Dry mucous membranes and no sweating</li>
<li>Blind as a bat - Blurred vision, mydriasis, cycloplegia</li>
<li>Mad as a hatter - Confusion</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Atropine Toxicity is dose-dependent<ul>
<li>++ Slight bradycardia <strong>and dry mouth</strong>/loss of sweating</li>
<li>+++ Dry mouth, thirst, increased heart rate, pupil dilation<h4 id="nicotinic-antagonists-nmj-blocks">Nicotinic Antagonists: NMJ blocks</h4>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Non-Depolarizing (curonium or curium) - competititve antag<ul>
<li>Pancuronium (long acting)</li>
<li>Rocuronium (intermediate)</li>
<li>Atracurium (intermediate)</li>
<li>Competitive antagonist</li>
<li>TI: Adjunct to general anesthesia. Facilitate intubation</li>
<li>AE: Hypotension, tachycardia, bronchospasms, respiratory paralysis, aspiration of gastrict contents</li>
<li><strong>Antidote: Effects reveresed by AChEi (neostigmine)</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Depolarizing:<ul>
<li><strong>Succinylcholine</strong> hydrolyzed by AChE and BuChE<ul>
<li>Persistent stimulation of nicotinic receptor at NMJ that leads to desensitization to ACh</li>
<li>TI: Induce muscle relaxation</li>
<li>AE: Muscle weakness, post-op myalgia, Hyperkalemia (<strong>life-threatening arrhythmias/cardiac arrest</strong> esp in pediatrics), malignant hyperthermia</li>
<li><strong>NOT REVERSIBLE BY AChEi</strong></li>
<li>Antidone is Sugammadex </li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="textbook-notes">Textbook Notes</h2>
<ol>
<li>Explain the difference between anticholinergic and antimuscarinic drugs.</li>
<li>Describe the mechanism of action and primary clinical use of Carbachol, Pilocarpine,Carbachol, Bethanechol, Methacholine, Varenicline, and Cevimeline.</li>
<li>List the symptoms of nicotine poisoning and explain why nicotine may have  cholinomimetic and cholinolytic effects.</li>
<li>List the main differences between the AChE inhibitors (AChEi) Neostigmine and Organophosphates (e.g., parathion).</li>
<li>Explain why the oximes are not always as effective as AChEi antidote.</li>
<li>List the primary clinical use of Pyridostigmine, Neostigmine, Donepezil, Rivastigmine, and Galantamine.</li>
<li>Explain the mechanisms triggered for the occurrence of “DUMBEELSS”.</li>
<li>List the main similarities and differences among Atropine, Scopolamine, Tiotropium, Tolterodine, Solifenacin, Desloratadine, Diphenhydramine.</li>
<li>List and explain the (“Antimuscarinic Syndrome”) poisoning signs/symptoms.</li>
<li>Explain the main differences between succinylcholine and ‘curoniums’.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Muscarine mimicked parasympathetic nerve dischage. Its effects were <strong>parasympathomimetic</strong></li>
<li>. The effects of acetylcholine itself and of other cholinomimetic drugs at autonomic neuroeffector junctions are called parasympathomimetic effects and are mediated by muscarinic receptors.</li>
<li>nicotine stimulated autonomic ganglia and skeletal muscle neuromuscular junctions but not autonomic effector cells. The <strong>ganglion and skeletal muscle receptors were therefore labeled nicotinic</strong>.</li>
<li>acetylcholine was later identified as the physiologic transmitter at both muscarinic and nicotinic receptors, both receptors were recognized as <strong>cholinoceptor subtypes.</strong></li>
<li>Direct-acting cholinomimetic agents bind to and activate muscarinic or nicotinic receptors</li>
<li>Indirect-acting agents produce their primary effects by inhibiting acetylcholinesterase.<ul>
<li>By inhibiting acetylcholinesterase, the indirect-acting drugs increase the endogenous acetylcholine concentration in synaptic clefts and neuroeffector junctions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>First, <em>acetylcholine released from parasympathetic nerves</em> <strong>activates</strong> muscarinic receptors on <strong>effector cells</strong> to alter organ function directly. </li>
<li>Second, <em>acetylcholine released from parasympathetic nerves</em> interacts with muscarinic receptors on <strong>nerve terminals</strong> to <strong>inhibit the release of their neurotransmitter</strong>. </li>
<li>Muscarinic agonist binding to <strong>M1, M3, and M5</strong> receptors activates the <strong>inositol trisphosphate (IP3), diacylglycerol (DAG)</strong> cascade.</li>
<li>Activation of <strong>M2 and M4</strong> muscarinic receptors <strong>inhibits adenylyl cyclase activity</strong> in tissues (eg, heart, intestine)</li>
<li>Continued presence of the nicotinic agonist <strong>prevents electrical recovery</strong> of the postjunctional membrane. Thus, a state of <strong>“depolarizing blockade”</strong> occurs initially during persistent agonist occupancy of the receptor. Continued agonist occupancy is associated with return of membrane voltage to the resting level. The receptor becomes <strong>desensitized</strong> to agonist, and this state is refractory to reversal by other agonists.</li>
<li><strong>Effects of direct-acting cholinoceptor stimulant</strong><ul>
<li>Sinoatrial node: <strong>Decrease in rate (negative chronotropy)</strong></li>
<li>Atria: <strong>Decrease in contractile strength (negative inotropy)</strong>. Decrease in refractory period</li>
<li>Atrioventricular node: <strong>Decrease in conduction velocity (negative dromotropy)</strong>. Increase in refractory period</li>
<li>Ventricles: Small decrease in contractile strength</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Chemotherapy II</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/chemotherapy-ii.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/chemotherapy-ii.html</id>
            <category term="Pharm"/>

        <updated>2020-12-06T17:05:32-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Anti-MetabolitePyrimidine ANtagonist: Cytarabine and GemcitabineToxicityPurine AntagonistTumor AntibioticsAnthracyclinesAnthracycline Mechanism:Antrhacycline CardiotoxicityAntrhacenedionesAntrhacenedione Mechanism:BleomycinBleomycin Mechanism:Bleomycin ToxicityTopoisomerase inhibitorsTopoisomerase I - Campthothecins: Topotecan and IrinotecanMechanism:Topoisomerase II -Podophyllotoxins: Etoposide and TeniposideMechanism:Microtubule InhibitorsTaxanes: Paclitaxel, Docetaxel, nab-PaclitaxelMechanism:Vinca Alkaloids: Vincristine, Vinorelbine, VinblastineMechanism:Adverse Effects:Drug Interactions:Targeted TherapiesTyrosine Kinase Inhibitors and Monoclonal AntibodiesTKIs “nibs” - Imatinib, Dasatinib, NilotinibMonoclonal&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <ul>
<li><a href="#anti-metabolite">Anti-Metabolite</a><ul>
<li><a href="#pyrimidine-antagonist-cytarabine-and-gemcitabine">Pyrimidine ANtagonist: Cytarabine and Gemcitabine</a><ul>
<li><a href="#toxicity">Toxicity</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#purine-antagonist">Purine Antagonist</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#tumor-antibiotics">Tumor Antibiotics</a><ul>
<li><a href="#anthracyclines">Anthracyclines</a><ul>
<li><a href="#anthracycline-mechanism">Anthracycline Mechanism:</a></li>
<li><a href="#antrhacycline-cardiotoxicity">Antrhacycline Cardiotoxicity</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#antrhacenediones">Antrhacenediones</a><ul>
<li><a href="#antrhacenedione-mechanism">Antrhacenedione Mechanism:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#bleomycin">Bleomycin</a><ul>
<li><a href="#bleomycin-mechanism">Bleomycin Mechanism:</a></li>
<li><a href="#bleomycin-toxicity">Bleomycin Toxicity</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#topoisomerase-inhibitors">Topoisomerase inhibitors</a><ul>
<li><a href="#topoisomerase-i---campthothecins-topotecan-and-irinotecan">Topoisomerase I - Campthothecins: Topotecan and Irinotecan</a><ul>
<li><a href="#mechanism">Mechanism:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#topoisomerase-ii--podophyllotoxins-etoposide-and-teniposide">Topoisomerase II -Podophyllotoxins: Etoposide and Teniposide</a><ul>
<li><a href="#mechanism-1">Mechanism:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#microtubule-inhibitors">Microtubule Inhibitors</a><ul>
<li><a href="#taxanes-paclitaxel-docetaxel-nab-paclitaxel">Taxanes: Paclitaxel, Docetaxel, nab-Paclitaxel</a><ul>
<li><a href="#mechanism-2">Mechanism:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#vinca-alkaloids-vincristine-vinorelbine-vinblastine">Vinca Alkaloids: Vincristine, Vinorelbine, Vinblastine</a><ul>
<li><a href="#mechanism-3">Mechanism:</a></li>
<li><a href="#adverse-effects">Adverse Effects:</a></li>
<li><a href="#drug-interactions">Drug Interactions:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapies</a></li>
<li><a href="#tyrosine-kinase-inhibitors-and-monoclonal-antibodies">Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors and Monoclonal Antibodies</a><ul>
<li><a href="#tkis-nibs---imatinib-dasatinib-nilotinib">TKIs “nibs” - Imatinib, Dasatinib, Nilotinib</a></li>
<li><a href="#monoclonal-antibodies---trastuzumab">Monoclonal Antibodies - Trastuzumab</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#hormone-receptor-modulators">Hormone Receptor Modulators</a><ul>
<li><a href="#estrogen-and-breast-cancer">Estrogen and Breast Cancer</a><ul>
<li><a href="#serm---tamoxifen">SERM - Tamoxifen</a></li>
<li><a href="#aromatase-inhibitors">Aromatase Inhibitors</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#epigenetic-modifiers">Epigenetic Modifiers</a><ul>
<li><a href="#hypomethylating-agents-azacitidine-and-decitabine">Hypomethylating Agents Azacitidine and Decitabine</a></li>
<li><a href="#histone-deacetylase-hdac-inhibitors---vorinostat-romidepsin-belinostat-panobinostat">Histone Deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors - Vorinostat, romidepsin, belinostat, panobinostat</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#--mild-myelosuppression">- Mild myelosuppression</a></li>
<li><a href="#immunomodulatory-drugs">Immunomodulatory Drugs</a><ul>
<li><a href="#immuno-blockade-therapy">Immuno Blockade Therapy</a><ul>
<li><a href="#ctla-4">CTLA-4:</a></li>
<li><a href="#pd1">PD1</a></li>
<li><a href="#side-effects-of-checkpoint-inhibitors">Side Effects of checkpoint inhibitors</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#miscellaneous">Miscellaneous</a><ul>
<li><a href="#l-asparaginase">L-Asparaginase</a></li>
<li><a href="#proteasome-inhibitors---bortezombi-and-carfilzomib">Proteasome Inhibitors - Bortezombi and Carfilzomib</a></li>
<li><a href="#dofferentiating-agents">Dofferentiating Agents</a></li>
<li><a href="#chemoprotectant-or-antidotes">Chemoprotectant or Antidotes</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="anti-metabolite">Anti-Metabolite</h2>
<p><strong>Anti-metabolites are specific for S phase</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Types:<ol>
<li>Folate Antagonist - methotrexate</li>
<li>Pyrimidine Antagonist - 5-FU</li>
<li>Purine Antagonist - 6-mercaptopurine<h3 id="pyrimidine-antagonist-cytarabine-and-gemcitabine">Pyrimidine ANtagonist: Cytarabine and Gemcitabine</h3>
Incorporate into cell and bind to DNA<h4 id="toxicity">Toxicity</h4>
Toxic to normal cells that proliferate rapidly<ul>
<li>GI</li>
<li>Bone marrow</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Dose dependent<ul>
<li>IV bolus dose: incorporate into RNA - more myelosuppression</li>
<li>IV continuous dose: incorporate into DNA - more skin toxicity <em>hand and foot syndrome</em></li>
<li>Prolonged administration damages DNA in epithelial cells of the skin.<ul>
<li>Hand and Foot:</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Gradual development of pain, redness, numbness and bilateral desquamation of palms<h3 id="purine-antagonist">Purine Antagonist</h3>
Fake purine bases.<ul>
<li>6-MP decoy for hypoxanthine</li>
<li>6-TG decoy for Guanine</li>
<li><strong>Require intracellular activation. Parent compount can cause toxicity</strong></li>
<li><strong>Reduce HGPRT enzyme activity</strong></li>
<li>6-TG is more potent</li>
<li><strong>6-TG causes more GI toxicity (more myelosuprressive)</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Allopurinol</strong> (drug for gout and tumor lysis syndrome) blocks xanthine oxidase and leads to <strong>accumulation of 6-MP</strong><ul>
<li><strong>Immunosuppressive</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tumor-antibiotics">Tumor Antibiotics</h2>
<p><strong>Specific for cells in G2 phase</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Anthracyclines: <strong>Doxorubicin, epirubicin</strong>, idarubicin, daunorubicin</li>
<li>Anthracenediones: Mitoxanthrone</li>
<li>Bleomycin</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Doxorubicin and epirubicin most active</strong> chemo drugs available<h3 id="anthracyclines">Anthracyclines</h3>
<h4 id="anthracycline-mechanism">Anthracycline Mechanism:</h4>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Intercalate between base pairs of DNA helix</strong> </p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inhibit topoisomerase II</strong> (<em>g2 phase</em>)</li>
<li><strong>Supercoiled DNA</strong></li>
<li><strong>Form free radicals</strong><h4 id="antrhacycline-cardiotoxicity">Antrhacycline Cardiotoxicity</h4>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cumulative cardiac toxicity</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Formation of ROS</strong></li>
<li><strong>Damage to Topo II in cardiomyocytes</strong><ul>
<li>Damage with all doses, but symptoms appear with <strong>cumulative exposure</strong></li>
<li>Liposome-encapsulated antrhacycline delay cardiotoxicity</li>
<li><strong>Chemoprotectant Dexrazoxane (DZR)</strong> <em>prevents cardiac injury</em> but <em>inhibits antitumor activity</em> of anthracyclines<h3 id="antrhacenediones">Antrhacenediones</h3>
<h4 id="antrhacenedione-mechanism">Antrhacenedione Mechanism:</h4>
Similar to anthracyclines</li>
<li><strong>DNA intercalataion and TOPO II inhibition</strong></li>
<li><strong>Free radical formation</strong> (<em>nitrogen dioxide</em>)</li>
<li><strong>NOT ROS</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Cardiotoxic, but delayed</strong><h3 id="bleomycin">Bleomycin</h3>
<h4 id="bleomycin-mechanism">Bleomycin Mechanism:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Bind to GC-rich portion of DNA and partially <strong>intercalate</strong></li>
<li><em>Bind divalent metals such as</em> <strong>iron, the active ligand</strong></li>
<li>Oxygen binds to iron and produce <strong>free radicals</strong></li>
<li>Free radicals make <strong>single-strand breaks</strong><h4 id="bleomycin-toxicity">Bleomycin Toxicity</h4>
</li>
<li><strong>Cumulative toxicity</strong></li>
<li>Detoxified by hydrolase</li>
<li>Hydrolase low in <strong>skin and lungs</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="topoisomerase-inhibitors">Topoisomerase inhibitors</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Specific for G2/S phase</strong><h3 id="topoisomerase-i---campthothecins-topotecan-and-irinotecan">Topoisomerase I - Campthothecins: Topotecan and Irinotecan</h3>
<h4 id="mechanism">Mechanism:</h4>
</li>
<li>Topo I relaxes supercoiled DNA</li>
<li>Inhibitors prevent this. Strands break, lead to apoptosis/</li>
<li><strong>S phase specific</strong></li>
<li><strong>Irinotecan has unique GI adverse effect</strong>:<ul>
<li><strong>Early-onset acute diarrhea - Cholinergic syndrome</strong></li>
<li>Delayed-onset diarrhea - Unknown mech.<h3 id="topoisomerase-ii--podophyllotoxins-etoposide-and-teniposide">Topoisomerase II -Podophyllotoxins: Etoposide and Teniposide</h3>
<h4 id="mechanism-1">Mechanism:</h4>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Pure Enzyme Inhibitors</strong> meaning <em>NO free radical formation or DNA intercalation</em></li>
<li>Inhibit TOPO II.<ul>
<li><strong>Halt progression out of S/G2 phase</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>GI toxicities and myelosuppression</em></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="microtubule-inhibitors">Microtubule Inhibitors</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Specific for M phase</strong><h3 id="taxanes-paclitaxel-docetaxel-nab-paclitaxel">Taxanes: Paclitaxel, Docetaxel, nab-Paclitaxel</h3>
<h4 id="mechanism-2">Mechanism:</h4>
</li>
<li><strong>Mitotic spindle poisons</strong></li>
<li><strong>Stabilize MT’s against depolymerization</strong></li>
<li><strong>Neurotoxic</strong></li>
<li><em>Myelosuppressive</em></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="vinca-alkaloids-vincristine-vinorelbine-vinblastine">Vinca Alkaloids: Vincristine, Vinorelbine, Vinblastine</h3>
<h4 id="mechanism-3">Mechanism:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Block mitotic cell division in M phase</strong></li>
<li>Bind to tubulin and <strong>inhibit polymerization MT’s</strong><h4 id="adverse-effects">Adverse Effects:</h4>
</li>
<li>MT’s are primary structural element of mitotic spindle in nerve structures</li>
<li><strong>Neurotoxicity</strong><ul>
<li><strong>Dose and schedule dependent</strong></li>
<li>Autonomic and cranial nerve neuropathy</li>
<li>Encephalopath</li>
<li><strong>Vinorelbine is least neurotoxic but causes more myelosuppression</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>GI autonomic dysfunction (<em>bloating, constipation, abd pain</em>) complicates therapy with vinca alkaloids<h4 id="drug-interactions">Drug Interactions:</h4>
</li>
<li><strong>Metabolic inhibitors</strong> can lead to <strong>overexposure</strong> to vinca alkaloid<ul>
<li><em>P450</em><h2 id="targeted-therapies">Targeted Therapies</h2>
Targeted Therapies attack specific molecular targets.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Very effective if specific target is driving cancer-</li>
<li>Less toxic that traditional-</li>
<li>Generally not curative as single agents-
Traditional vs Targeted:</li>
<li>Reduce mortality</li>
<li>Stop disease progression</li>
<li>More toxic<h2 id="tyrosine-kinase-inhibitors-and-monoclonal-antibodies">Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors and Monoclonal Antibodies</h2>
<h3 id="tkis-nibs---imatinib-dasatinib-nilotinib">TKIs “nibs” - Imatinib, Dasatinib, Nilotinib</h3>
</li>
<li>Imatinib used for CML. Inhibit proliferation of bcr-abl fusion prot.<ul>
<li><strong>Binds to ATP binding pocket of Tyr kinase</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>TKI’s are part of normal cellular pathways</li>
<li>Inhbition of TKI can cause <strong>off-target</strong> effects:<ul>
<li>MoA has unintended organ insults</li>
<li>Myelosuppression<h3 id="monoclonal-antibodies---trastuzumab">Monoclonal Antibodies - Trastuzumab</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>MAB that targets Her2/neu receptor.
<strong>- HER2/neu is also expressed in cardiomyocytes</strong> - which explains <strong>off-target cardiotoxicity</strong>  <h2 id="hormone-receptor-modulators">Hormone Receptor Modulators</h2>
<h3 id="estrogen-and-breast-cancer">Estrogen and Breast Cancer</h3>
Estrogen fuels growth of breast cancer cells</li>
<li>Inhibitors:<ul>
<li>Pre menopause: Selective Estrogen Receptor Modulators <strong>SERMs</strong> - <strong>Tamoxifen</strong></li>
<li>Post menopause: <strong>Aromatase Inhibitors</strong> - <strong>Exemestane</strong></li>
<li>Average age of menoupause is 51 yrs.<h4 id="serm---tamoxifen">SERM - Tamoxifen</h4>
75% of breast cancer epxpress estrogen receptors <em>ER+</em>, 65% express progesterone receptors <em>PR+</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Tamoxifen for hormonal therapy:<ul>
<li>Prodrug. <strong>Hydroxymetabolites</strong> provide the anti-tumor activity.</li>
<li>Partial estrogen agonist</li>
<li>Antagonist in breast tissue</li>
<li>Can prevent breast cancer in high risk PT and treat those with advanced or localized disease</li>
<li><strong>Adverse</strong>: Due to estrogenic effects - Uterine Cancer<h4 id="aromatase-inhibitors">Aromatase Inhibitors</h4>
<code>Exemestane, Letrozole, Anastrozole – Inhibit the enzyme aromatase ONLY in peripheral tissue (NOT in ovaries) so only useful in post-menopausal women</code><h2 id="epigenetic-modifiers">Epigenetic Modifiers</h2>
<h3 id="hypomethylating-agents-azacitidine-and-decitabine">Hypomethylating Agents Azacitidine and Decitabine</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Inhibit DNA methyltransferases</strong><ul>
<li>Hypomethylation</li>
<li>Apoptosis</li>
<li>Reverse epigenetic silencing</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Need to be incorporated into DNA through reduced metabolite<ul>
<li>One cycle of replication gets hemimethylated. Two cycles for entire demthylation.</li>
<li><strong>Several doses</strong> are needed for clinical response.<ul>
<li>At high doses it acts like anti-pyrimidine (<em>cytotoxic and anti-metabolite</em>)<h3 id="histone-deacetylase-hdac-inhibitors---vorinostat-romidepsin-belinostat-panobinostat">Histone Deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors - Vorinostat, romidepsin, belinostat, panobinostat</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>HDAC catalyzes <strong>removal of acetyl groups</strong> from histones.<ul>
<li>DNA wraps more tightle when acetyl groups are removed. Silenced, euchromatin.</li>
<li>This prevents the expression of <strong>tumor suppressor genes</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>HDAC inhibitors bind to the enzyme and prevent it.</li>
<li>Increased acetylation of DNA, and <strong>expression of the silenced genes</strong></li>
<li><strong>Adverse Effects</strong>:<ul>
<li>Cardiac Toxicity</li>
<li>GI Tox</li>
<li>Mild myelosuppression</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="immunomodulatory-drugs">Immunomodulatory Drugs</h2>
<h3 id="immuno-blockade-therapy">Immuno Blockade Therapy</h3>
<pre><code>T cell activation requires two signals: TCR and B7/CD28 co-stim. 
In normal situations, T cell de-activate themselves by binding their CTLA4 receptor to CD80 on DCs. 
PD1 pathway delivers inhibitory signals to immune system to slow down. Limits initiation and duration of immune response. When a T cell activates it induces PD1 expression.
Production if IFNg also upregulates PD1L, which binds to PD1 and turns it off.
Tumor cells evade by either upregulating the PD1L or by upregulating CD80 and binding T cell CTLA4, downregulating them, or by hiding CD28.</code></pre><ul>
<li>Anti-CTLA4: Ipilimumbab</li>
<li>Anti-PD1: Pembrolizumab, Nivolumab</li>
<li>Anti-PD1L: Atezolizumab, Avelumab, Durvalumab<h4 id="ctla-4">CTLA-4:</h4>
</li>
<li>Receptors are distributed through secondary lymphoid organs</li>
<li>Target recently primed T cells</li>
<li>Phosphatases SHP1,2, PP2a</li>
<li>Inhibit glycolysis<h4 id="pd1">PD1</h4>
</li>
<li>Inflamed peripheral tissue and secondary lymphoid organs</li>
<li>Target Effector T cells</li>
<li>Phosphatase SHP2</li>
<li>Inhibit Glycolysis and induce Fatty Acid Oxidation<h4 id="side-effects-of-checkpoint-inhibitors">Side Effects of checkpoint inhibitors</h4>
</li>
<li>They can cause autoimmune side effects<ul>
<li>MAB’s are highly specific, so not an issue of off-target toxicities</li>
<li><strong>Substantial on-target toxiciites possible</strong><ul>
<li>Pembrolizumab therapy caused thyroiditis and thyroid dysfunction</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Majority of cases result in irreversible hypothyroidism</li>
<li>Similar issues of thyroid dysfunction observed in melanoma
– Other immune related adverse events can occur with systemic administration of immune checkpoint inhibitors </li>
<li>dermatologic, gastrointestinal, hepatic, endocrine inflammatory events </li>
<li>temporary immunosuppression with corticosteroids, TNFα antagonists, or other agents effective in most cases but can be fatal</li>
<li>Dermatitis, Colitis, Hepatitis</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Side Effects of CAR T therapy:<ul>
<li>Cytokine Release Syndrome<ul>
<li>When the CAR T cell engages surrogate antigens it releases a variety of cytokines that get picked up by macrophages and other innate immune cells.</li>
<li>They go nuts for it and start shitting the bed too.</li>
<li>CAR T cells are able to get into CSF, and it is possible that their cytokine release would make the BBB permeable to more CAR T cells and other immune cells.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Neurotoxicity, Hemodynamic instability (tachycardia, hypotension, capillary leak) Organ Dysfunction (AST and ALT elevation, Hyperbilirubinemia, Respiratory Failure)<h2 id="miscellaneous">Miscellaneous</h2>
<h3 id="l-asparaginase">L-Asparaginase</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>L-Asparaginase is specific for G1 phase</strong></li>
<li>All cells require Asparagine</li>
<li>Normal cells, but <strong>NOT ALL</strong> cells can synthesize their own.</li>
<li>Hydrolysis of L-aspargine derprives tumor cells of the necessary amino acid.</li>
<li>Used to treat ALL (<em>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</em>)</li>
<li><strong>Must be adminstered within 9-10 days before OR 24 hours after treatment with antifolate methotrexate</strong><ul>
<li>Concurrent asparginase use can block methotrexate (S phase) activity by inhibitin cell replication and inhibiting glutaminatinase <em>which methotrexate requires for optimal accumulation</em><ul>
<li>Aspariginase before methotrexate is <strong>ANTAGONISTIC</strong></li>
<li>Methotrexate before asparaginase may be <strong>SYNERGYSTIC</strong><h3 id="proteasome-inhibitors---bortezombi-and-carfilzomib">Proteasome Inhibitors - Bortezombi and Carfilzomib</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Normall cells the proteasome degrades intracellular proteins and maintains homeostasis</li>
<li><strong>Myeloma</strong> cells can be effectively <strong>killed by proteasome inhibitors</strong></li>
<li><strong>Bortezomib</strong> binds <strong>reversibly</strong> to proteasome</li>
<li><strong>Carfilzomib</strong> binds <strong>irreversibly</strong></li>
<li>Inhibition of proteasome leads to an accumulation of protein in tumor cells that lead to cell death through the unfolded protein pathway.</li>
<li>Proteasome inhibitors also inhibit NF-KB that is common in cancer cells.</li>
<li><strong>Adverse Effects</strong>:<ul>
<li>Peripheral neuropathy (reversible)</li>
<li>Myelosuppresion</li>
<li>Mild Gi effects<h3 id="dofferentiating-agents">Dofferentiating Agents</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>High tumor grades are poorly differentiated</li>
<li>Alternative to inducing apoptosis</li>
<li>Limited success EXCEPT: <ul>
<li>ATRA or ATO for APL</li>
<li>9-cis RA - regression of premalignant lesions in mouth and throat.<h3 id="chemoprotectant-or-antidotes">Chemoprotectant or Antidotes</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Amifostine (PRODRUG)</strong> - activated by alkaline phosphatases that are <strong>NOT</strong> on cancer cells.</li>
<li>Scavenges <strong>free radicals</strong> and prevents <strong>cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity</strong></li>
<li><strong>MESNA prevents cyclophosphamide</strong> toxicity <strong>hemorrhagic cystitis</strong> by inactivating <strong>acrolein</strong></li>
<li><strong>Methylene blue</strong> treats <strong>CNS toxicity</strong> caused by <strong>ifosamide</strong> by inhibiting <strong>chloroacetaldehyde</strong></li>
<li><strong>Dexrazoxane prevents cardiotoxicity by anthracycline</strong> by <strong>chelating iron</strong> and preventing hyrdoxyl radicals</li>
<li><strong>Folinic Acid (leocovorin) reduces methotrexate</strong> toxicity <strong>but enhances</strong> effect of pyrimidine antagonist <strong>5-FU</strong> by <em>inhibiting thymidylate synthase</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Chemotherapy I</title>
        <author>
            <name>William Slattery</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/chemotherapy-i.html"/>
        <id>https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/chemotherapy-i.html</id>
            <category term="Pharm"/>

        <updated>2020-12-06T17:05:24-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Chemotherapy IHallmarks of CancerChallengesMultiple mutationsHeterogeneityEpigeneticsTumor MicroenvironmentDrug Resistance:Chemotherapy:History:Types of ChemoTargetting the Cell CycleTherapeutic WindowDrug Resistance: Goldie-Coldman ModelCombination ChemotherapyRoute of Administration - 5-FUPharmacokineticsAlkylating AgentsAlkylating Mustards:General Mechanism:Reactivity:Notes on MustardsAlkylating Mustards: Cyclophosphamide and Ifosfamide are pro-drugsAlkylating Mustards: Cyclophosphamide and Ifosfamide and acrolein toxicityAlkylating Mustards: Ifosfamide Neurotoxicity:Alkylating NitrosoureasAlkylating TriazenesAlkylating Platinum&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <ul>
<li><a href="#chemotherapy-i">Chemotherapy I</a><ul>
<li><a href="#hallmarks-of-cancer">Hallmarks of Cancer</a><ul>
<li><a href="#challenges">Challenges</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#multiple-mutations">Multiple mutations</a></li>
<li><a href="#heterogeneity">Heterogeneity</a></li>
<li><a href="#epigenetics">Epigenetics</a></li>
<li><a href="#tumor-microenvironment">Tumor Microenvironment</a></li>
<li><a href="#drug-resistance">Drug Resistance:</a><ul>
<li><a href="#chemotherapy">Chemotherapy:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#history">History:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#types-of-chemo">Types of Chemo</a><ul>
<li><a href="#targetting-the-cell-cycle">Targetting the Cell Cycle</a></li>
<li><a href="#therapeutic-window">Therapeutic Window</a></li>
<li><a href="#drug-resistance-goldie-coldman-model">Drug Resistance: Goldie-Coldman Model</a></li>
<li><a href="#combination-chemotherapy">Combination Chemotherapy</a></li>
<li><a href="#route-of-administration---5-fu">Route of Administration - 5-FU</a></li>
<li><a href="#pharmacokinetics">Pharmacokinetics</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#alkylating-agents">Alkylating Agents</a><ul>
<li><a href="#alkylating-mustards">Alkylating Mustards:</a><ul>
<li><a href="#general-mechanism">General Mechanism:</a></li>
<li><a href="#reactivity">Reactivity:</a></li>
<li><a href="#notes-on-mustards">Notes on Mustards</a><ul>
<li><a href="#alkylating-mustards-cyclophosphamide-and-ifosfamide-are-pro-drugs">Alkylating Mustards: <strong>Cyclophosphamide and Ifosfamide</strong> are <strong>pro-drugs</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="#alkylating-mustards-cyclophosphamide-and-ifosfamide-and-acrolein-toxicity">Alkylating Mustards: <strong>Cyclophosphamide and Ifosfamide</strong> and acrolein toxicity</a></li>
<li><a href="#alkylating-mustards-ifosfamide-neurotoxicity">Alkylating Mustards: Ifosfamide Neurotoxicity:</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#alkylating-nitrosoureas">Alkylating Nitrosoureas</a></li>
<li><a href="#alkylating-triazenes">Alkylating Triazenes</a></li>
<li><a href="#alkylating-platinum-complexes">Alkylating Platinum Complexes</a></li>
<li><a href="#alkylating-miscellaneous-procarbazine">Alkylating Miscellaneous: Procarbazine</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#summary-of-alkylating">Summary of Alkylating:</a></li>
<li><a href="#summary-of-alkylating-agent-toxicity">Summary of Alkylating Agent Toxicity:</a><h2 id="chemotherapy-i">Chemotherapy I</h2>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Oncogene vs Tumor Suppressor | Gain of Function vs Loss of Function</li>
<li>Treating oncogenes the goal is to suppress<ul>
<li>e.g. Tyrosine kinase inhibitor</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Treating suppressor genes goal is to activate<ul>
<li>e.g. MAB cetuximab, which activates p53.<h4 id="hallmarks-of-cancer">Hallmarks of Cancer</h4>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Sustained proliferation</li>
<li>Evade growth suppressors</li>
<li>Enable replicative immortality</li>
<li>Resist celld eath</li>
<li>Activate invastion and metastasis</li>
<li>Induce angiogenesis</li>
<li>Genome instability and mutation</li>
<li>Avoid immune destruction</li>
<li>Deregulate cellular metabolism</li>
<li>Tumor promoting inflammation</li>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/target.JPG" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/target-xs.JPG 300w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/target-sm.JPG 480w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/target-md.JPG 768w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/target-lg.JPG 1024w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/target-xl.JPG 1360w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/target-2xl.JPG 1600w"  alt="Targetting Cancer" width="716" height="528" /></figure><h3 id="challenges">Challenges</h3>
<h4 id="multiple-mutations">Multiple mutations</h4>
<h4 id="heterogeneity">Heterogeneity</h4>
<ul>
<li>2/3 of mutation from single biopsy not detected in different regions of the same tumor<h4 id="epigenetics">Epigenetics</h4>
</li>
<li>Normal cells acquire gentic and epigenetic alterations</li>
<li>Trying to treat cancer can exert additional pressure that accerlates its development of resistant</li>
<li>Epigenetic therapy can reverse these and restore sensitivity to treatment</li>
<li>Epigenetic targets enzymes - less toxic than chemo.</li>
<li><strong>Great if use in combination therapy</strong><h4 id="tumor-microenvironment">Tumor Microenvironment</h4>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Multiple cell types that support tumor growth<ul>
<li><strong>Immune cells</strong></li>
<li><strong>Fibroblasts</strong></li>
<li><strong>Endothelial cells</strong></li>
<li><strong>Vasculature</strong></li>
<li><em>Pancreatic cancer is not majorally cancerous cells, large portion is *</em>fibroblast***</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>These microenvironment cells are all <strong>targetable</strong><h4 id="drug-resistance">Drug Resistance:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>P-glycoprotein efflux pumps</strong> extrude chemotherapy drugs</li>
<li>Drug metabolism</li>
<li>Drug sequestration</li>
<li>Alter signal transduction pathways</li>
<li>Evade or ignore programmed cell death<h3 id="chemotherapy">Chemotherapy:</h3>
</li>
<li>Dev 1940-1960 for solid tumors, hematological malignancies</li>
<li>Integrated with surgery and radiation</li>
<li>Obstacles: <ul>
<li>R</li>
<li>Hurt normal cells   <h4 id="history">History:</h4>
</li>
<li>Mechlorethamine</li>
<li>Anti-metabolites<ul>
<li>Methotrexate and 5-fu</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Vinca Alkaloid</li>
<li>Cisplatin to inhibit cell division and cure solid tumors</li>
<li>Cure of Hodgkin’s disease and ALL</li>
<li>Adjuvant chemotherapy</li>
<li>Cure of testicular cancer (vinblastine + bleomycin + cisplatin)</li>
<li>Targeted Therapy:<ul>
<li>Gleevec - RTK for CML</li>
<li>Rituximab - NHL<h2 id="types-of-chemo">Types of Chemo</h2>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Primary Induction</strong><ul>
<li><strong>advanced and no alternative</strong></li>
<li>Palliative</li>
<li><strong>Improve quality of life</strong></li>
<li>Prolong time to tumor progression (TTP)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Neoaduvnat</strong><pre><code>- localized cancer
- Not completely effective
- Used when surgery is not possible</code></pre></li>
<li><strong>Adjuvant</strong><pre><code>- follow surgery and radiation
- Reduce incidence of local and systemic recurrence
- **Improve overall survival** **OS**
- **Prolong disease free survival** **DFS**</code></pre><h3 id="targetting-the-cell-cycle">Targetting the Cell Cycle</h3>
</li>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/CELLCYCLE.png" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/CELLCYCLE-xs.png 300w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/CELLCYCLE-sm.png 480w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/CELLCYCLE-md.png 768w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/CELLCYCLE-lg.png 1024w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/CELLCYCLE-xl.png 1360w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/CELLCYCLE-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="Cell Cycle" width="1498" height="779" /></figure></li>
<li>Cell survival exponentially related to dose</li>
<li>Slope of curve related to rate of cell proliferation</li>
<li><strong>Effective</strong> against those cells that <strong>proliferate rapidly</strong></li>
<li>Cause of Side Effects<ul>
<li><strong>Bone marrow</strong> stem cells: Immunocompromise</li>
<li>GI mucosal cells: </li>
<li>Hair Follicles: Alopecia</li>
<li>Ovaries testes<h3 id="therapeutic-window">Therapeutic Window</h3>
</li>
<li>Goals are to maximize efficacy and limit tocicity</li>
<li>Usually use maximum tolerated dose<h3 id="drug-resistance-goldie-coldman-model">Drug Resistance: Goldie-Coldman Model</h3>
<ul>
<li>Drug resistance probability is dependednt on intrinsic genetic instabillity</li>
<li>Even the <em>smallest detectable tumor contains at least 1 drug-resistant clone</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Use all effective chemo drugs</strong><h3 id="combination-chemotherapy">Combination Chemotherapy</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/combo.JPG" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/combo-xs.JPG 300w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/combo-sm.JPG 480w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/combo-md.JPG 768w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/combo-lg.JPG 1024w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/combo-xl.JPG 1360w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/combo-2xl.JPG 1600w"  alt="Combo" width="1578" height="906" /></figure><h3 id="route-of-administration---5-fu">Route of Administration - 5-FU</h3>
</li>
<li>IV bolus dose vs IV continuous infusion<ul>
<li>IV Bolous: Incorporate into cellular RNA and myelosuppression</li>
<li>IV Continuous: Incorporate into cellular DNA but skin toxicity</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Intermittent dose<ul>
<li>600mg/m2/cycle</li>
<li>No cardiac or bladder toxicity</li>
<li>Secondary malignancies can develop</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Single high dose<ul>
<li>Cardiac toxicity</li>
<li>Hemorrhagic cystitis</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Daily Dose<ul>
<li>Hemorrhagic cystitis</li>
<li>Secondary Malignancies<h3 id="pharmacokinetics">Pharmacokinetics</h3>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Phramocokinetics represents the kinetics of accumulation and disapperance from plasma</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="alkylating-agents">Alkylating Agents</h2>
<ul>
<li>Classes:<ol>
<li><strong>Nitrogen mustards</strong></li>
<li><strong>Nitrosoureas</strong></li>
<li><strong>Triazenes</strong></li>
<li><strong>Platinum complexes</strong><h3 id="alkylating-mustards">Alkylating Mustards:</h3>
<h4 id="general-mechanism">General Mechanism:</h4>
</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Drug activated into <em>reative intermediates</em> that <strong>form adducts</strong> at N7 position of guanine in DNA</li>
<li>Loss of the guanine base (<em>depurination</em>) or miscoding of abnormal base pairing</li>
<li>Strand break or cross-linking of DNA</li>
<li>Cell death</li>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/alkylate.JPG" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/alkylate-xs.JPG 300w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/alkylate-sm.JPG 480w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/alkylate-md.JPG 768w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/alkylate-lg.JPG 1024w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/alkylate-xl.JPG 1360w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/alkylate-2xl.JPG 1600w"  alt="Alkylate" width="876" height="659" /></figure><pre><code>Alkylating groups on nitrogen mustard act as &quot;warhead&quot;
N7 on guanine acts as electron donor, forming adduct
React with 2nd guanine, leading to depurination</code></pre><h4 id="reactivity">Reactivity:</h4>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Reactivity can be reduced by adding aromatic ring to warhead.</li>
<li>Less reactivity allows for drug to be given orally.<ul>
<li>Elderly patients with multiple myeloma or CLL<h4 id="notes-on-mustards">Notes on Mustards</h4>
<h5 id="alkylating-mustards-cyclophosphamide-and-ifosfamide-are-pro-drugs">Alkylating Mustards: <strong>Cyclophosphamide and Ifosfamide</strong> are <strong>pro-drugs</strong></h5>
</li>
<li>Share same active cytotoxic ingredient: phophoramide mustard</li>
<li>Both metabolized to <strong>acrolein</strong> (toxic to bladder - <strong>hemorrhagic cystitis</strong>)<h5 id="alkylating-mustards-cyclophosphamide-and-ifosfamide-and-acrolein-toxicity">Alkylating Mustards: <strong>Cyclophosphamide and Ifosfamide</strong> and acrolein toxicity</h5>
</li>
<li>Hemorrhagic cystitis is dose and schedule dependent</li>
<li>Acreolin react with nucleophiles in uroepithelium:<ul>
<li>Prevent with adequate hydration or MESNA</li>
<li>MESNA inactivates acrolein by binding to and preventing reaction with cellular nucleophiles</li>
<li>MESNA can prevent hemorrhagic cystitis, but not treat it.</li>
<li>Treatment is hydration with saline</li>
<li><strong>Blood in urine of PT treated with cyclophosphamide</strong> is an early warning sign of bladder tox.<h5 id="alkylating-mustards-ifosfamide-neurotoxicity">Alkylating Mustards: Ifosfamide Neurotoxicity:</h5>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Ifosfamide shares hemorrhagic cystits toxicity with cyclophosphamide - <strong>acrolein</strong></li>
<li>Also has Unique CNS neurotoxicity: <ul>
<li>Chloroacetaldehyde distrub mitochondrial respiratory chain</li>
<li><strong>Methylene blue is the antidote</strong>. Inhibits formation of <strong>chloroacetaldehyde</strong></li>
<li><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/ifosamide.JPG" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/ifosamide-xs.JPG 300w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/ifosamide-sm.JPG 480w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/ifosamide-md.JPG 768w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/ifosamide-lg.JPG 1024w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/ifosamide-xl.JPG 1360w ,https://BGASM.github.io/medNotes/media/posts/9/responsive/ifosamide-2xl.JPG 1600w"  alt="Ifosamide" width="871" height="657" /></figure><h4 id="alkylating-nitrosoureas">Alkylating Nitrosoureas</h4>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Liberate organic isocyanates</li>
<li>React with lysine residues</li>
<li>Inactivation of protein, esp DNA repair enzyme</li>
<li><strong>Highly lipophillic</strong> and used to treat brain tumor because <strong>cross BBB</strong><h4 id="alkylating-triazenes">Alkylating Triazenes</h4>
</li>
<li><strong>Methylate</strong> DNA at O6 and N7 positions on <strong>Guanine</strong></li>
<li>Temozolamide is <strong>highly lipophillic</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4 id="alkylating-platinum-complexes">Alkylating Platinum Complexes</h4>
<ul>
<li>React with DNA to produce inter and intra strand crosslinnks between adjacent guanines, or guanine and adeninge</li>
<li>Produce <strong>DNA adducts</strong> that inhibit replication and transcription</li>
<li><strong>Cisplatin, Carboplatin</strong>: <ul>
<li>Good for <strong>neck cancer</strong>. </li>
<li>Cistplatin has <strong>High nephrotoxicity</strong></li>
<li>Carboplatin has <strong>low nephrotoxicity</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Oxaliplatin: <ul>
<li>More effective for <strong>colon and pancreatic</strong></li>
</ul>
<strong>- Nephrotoxicity</strong></li>
<li>Oxaliplatin more potent than cisplatin in vitro and requires fewer DNA adducts to achieve cytotoxicity</li>
<li>Carboplatin is a larger molecule than cisplatin; longer retention and different toxicities (less)</li>
<li><strong>Cytotoxic activity against different tumors and toxicity NOT the same with different platinum compounds</strong><h4 id="alkylating-miscellaneous-procarbazine">Alkylating Miscellaneous: Procarbazine</h4>
</li>
<li>MAOI: MAO - Inhibitor<h3 id="summary-of-alkylating">Summary of Alkylating:</h3>
</li>
<li>Share similar mechanism of action:<ul>
<li>Activated to reactive</li>
<li>Form adducts with cellular macromolecules</li>
<li>Methylkate DNA
gernate isocyanates</li>
<li>Same adverse effects:</li>
<li>Hemorrhagic cystitis</li>
<li>CNS toxicity</li>
<li>Nephrotoxicity and neuropathy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lipophillic agents have unique applications<h3 id="summary-of-alkylating-agent-toxicity">Summary of Alkylating Agent Toxicity:</h3>
<ul>
<li>More toxic to normal, rapidly proliferating cells</li>
<li>Non-cell cycle specific</li>
<li>Damage DNA</li>
<li>Increase mutations</li>
<li>Secondary malignancies are long-term<ul>
<li>Leukemias</li>
<li>Myelodysplastic syndrome</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
